<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>The Uncommon Engineer Blog</title>
        <link>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog</link>
        <description>The Uncommon Engineer Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Masks Off: 2025 in Review]]></title>
            <link>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/masks-off-2025-in-review</link>
            <guid>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/masks-off-2025-in-review</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Year-end review analyzing power consolidation imperial impunity and inherent untrustworthiness of tech industry leadership. Essential reading for understanding ]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Masks Off: 2025 in Review" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/masks-off-2025-2003a7b132aa617c4e950d42f940aeed.jpg" width="1920" height="1076" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Talofa reader,</p>
<p>To say 2025 was a 'challenging year' would be the understatement of understatements. No, it wasn't challenging—it was full-on "masks off": power consolidation and imperial impunity on full display.</p>
<p>Yes, it's going to be one of those newsletters.</p>
<p>It's that wonderful, magical time of year where we get to reflect on everything that happened for us this year. The highs, the lows, the lessons learned and friends we made along the way. But in my heart of hearts, or at least if I'm getting it one hundred, I don't feel that way. At all.</p>
<p>It's hard to put into words sometimes, the feeling I have when I look at everything around us. The economic position I've lived in for so many years has shielded me and my family from much of what I see in the news—the cost of living crisis, the housing shortage, the job market collapse.</p>
<p>But (believe it or not) I'm human. I don't want to see people struggle for the basics, I don't want to see some people have nothing, while others have way more than they would ever need. And having another individually optimistic piece from some tech bro at Amazon is a little too on the nose for me.</p>
<p>Fortunately, I've never been mistaken for an optimistic person, so you're going to get the complete opposite here. And I don't think being cynical or all "doom &amp; gloom" is hot shit either. No-one's trying to be the cool contrarian guy here cause it's "edgy"—those types have always been lame, they just didn't know it.</p>
<p>I'm going to say some things because a) it's genuinely how I feel about it and b) it's actually real and happening right now, and my position is- we can keep brushing past it with our head in the sand while it doesn't affect us "that much", or we can actually talk about it so I know where you stand (note: not wanting to talk about it, or acknowledge it, is 100% a position).</p>
<p>What's this got to do with AI, CyberSecurity or Tech? In my opinion, everything.</p>
<p>You want examples? Look around aka get your head out of your ass:</p>
<p>A handful of companies now control the entire AI landscape—OpenAI, Anthropic, and Google are <a href="https://time.com/7322418/chat-gpt-open-ai-nvidia-tech-monopoly/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">consolidating power</a> while extracting human creativity and labour at scale. As TIME puts it:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>"If lawmakers fail to act, the future of AI will be written not by open competition or bold new ideas, but by the same handful of firms that already dominate."</em></p>
<p>— Asad Ramzanali</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Meanwhile, <a href="https://news.crunchbase.com/startups/tech-layoffs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">126,352 tech workers were laid off in 2025</a> while profits continued to soar. Does that feel like "survival of the company" actions, or pure extraction?</p>
<p>Here in Aotearoa, our anti-Māori coalition government has done a bang-up job of the economy (note: sarcasm). <a href="https://business.scoop.co.nz/2025/12/16/national-is-making-life-more-expensive/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Bread is up 53%, milk up 16%, sirloin beef up 27%</a>. Nearly 200 Kiwis leave the country every day. The neoliberal project is delivering exactly what it's designed to: transfer wealth upward while working class and Pasifika communities pay for the privilege.</p>
<p>Globally, democratic institutions are collapsing in real-time. <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/world/europe/far-right-populists-top-polls-germany-france-britain-first-time-rcna224706" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Far-right parties lead polls in Germany, France, and the UK simultaneously</a>—the first time in modern history. <a href="https://carnegieendowment.org/research/2025/09/the-european-radical-right-in-the-age-of-trump-20" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Trump administration openly endorses European far-right movements</a>. And probably the sickest reality check for the facade of "international law" and "Western values": <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gaza_genocide" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The International Association of Genocide Scholars declared Israel is committing genocide in Gaza</a>—over 66,000 Palestinians killed by October 2025, half of them women and children. And the climate? <a href="https://www.who.int/news/item/29-10-2025-climate-inaction-is-claiming-millions-of-lives-every-year--warns-new-lancet-countdown-report" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">546,000 people die annually from heat</a>, a 23% increase since the 1990s. <a href="https://time.com/7329105/lancet-health-climate-impacts-2025/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Another 2.5 million die yearly from fossil fuel air pollution</a>. The bodies stack up while we're still debating individual carbon footprints.</p>
<p>We could talk about "seasons" or how this is just cyclical, but I would argue this isn't about things going through their natural progression, this is structural. The way the world has been built and rebuilt post-WW2—how the global north exploits and extracts from the global south—most people have no idea what I'm talking about right now. And that's the issue. The very structure and mechanisms by which our society operates and runs today isn't "flawed"—it's designed to deliver exactly what we see. It reminds me of W. Edwards Deming's famous quote*"Every system is perfectly designed to get the result that it does."*</p>
<p>We could talk about neoliberalism, white supremacy, fascism, and far-right ideology—and we'd essentially be talking about the same thing. Most of this is outside the scope of this essay, but I wanted to put those keywords in the frame so you start to think about how deep these things go- what you see and hear every day, to what has been built and forged in local and international systems for millennia.</p>
<p>Now, do you think individual optimism and adaptability is going to get the job done of systemic change (the thing that's needed)? Straight up, all of that shit is gaslighting. I know this shit's heavy. To even think about it, for a lot of us, is to remind ourselves how overwhelming and futile it feels to go against the grain. I'm right there with you, but that doesn't make these things any less true. And even that right there, that feeling (that it's futile)... is also gaslighting.</p>
<p>Why? Because people are powerful.</p>
<p>People working together, with other people, looking out for each other and being there for each other- is the most powerful thing in the world. Bar none. Powerful institutions and people in positions of power know this- which is why they must divide, disarm, and disempower people. Reminds me of the story of the Tower of Babel. I'm paraphrasing here, but a whole bunch of people got together, co-ordinated and collaborated and built a tower that stretched into the sky, almost reaching the heavens and God panicked and cast a spell on all the people where they all spoke different languages so couldn't understand each other. And thus, thwarted the Tower of Babel. See the theme there? A God, had to divide the people in order not to be overthrown (again, paraphrasing and oversimplifying).</p>
<blockquote>
<p>What's the link to this AI, and Tech?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Other than the obvious—AI's many issues with extraction, intellectual property and copyright violations, bias, toxicity and harms to Indigenous communities, climate and water usage—other than<em><strong>those</strong></em>... of the many things to choose from, one quote from an ex-meta engineer hit home for me, in terms of this power, people, and the distracting or diversion tactic:</p>
<p>❝"The best minds of my generation are thinking about how to make people click ads. That sucks."</p>
<p>— Jeff Hammerbacher (ex-Meta engineer)I get it. These private sector, for-profit jobs pay the best. They tend to have the better resources, perks, compensation—all-round things that make this life<em>better</em>. So of course they're going to get the lion's share of people, usually the most brilliant people at that.</p>
<p>So the most powerful companies, get the most talented people, using human societies best skills... to make people click ads.</p>
<p>That's the link.</p>
<p>So. What do we do with all this? Fuck knows- is my initial response. Not because I don't know, or don't have ideas or feelings about it. But honestly, I'm a little bit tired of thinking about it all the time. Sure, we're not all the same in how we approach, implement or philosophise life, so this is just a little insight in how I operate and how I see and analyse the world. It's how I've done it for as long as I can remember. Since intermediate, high school and every year after. Before I knew anything about anything, I knew something was off—at least from my vantage point. So everything I've learned since—via formal education, self-study, or lived experience—it's just tiring seeing the matrix this long and while the crumbs of improvement have been flicked off the table towards us to appease us, the exploitation and extraction machine soldiers on, gaining power, racking up the body count.</p>
<p>Bleak. Hahahaha. Yes, bleak.</p>
<p>But at least if we start there—not out of despair, but out of being tired of the facade and wanting to do something about it. I'm in tech, I'm a technologist, so my call to action isn't even that radical (depending on your definition or level of severity to achieve radical status)—it's to tech people to start being honest with themselves about their place in this system, because I'm done with us pretending we're not contributing to every calamity or disaster around us. I understand it maybe comes from a place of survival, of minding our business because it doesn't affect us and we're "lucky" to be shielded from it. I totally get that. But let's not bullshit ourselves and others that we don't know the impact of what we're a part of. I think I respect a position of knowing we're the stormtroopers of the Death Star, rather than convincing ourselves we have anything to do with the resistance because we helped an underrepresented group play with some big tech technology a couple of times a year.</p>
<p>2026 is going to be the year of not doing the corporate talking points anymore. It's about finding the people and causes that can build alternative power structures. We stop living in the corporate tech bro shared fantasy that we're helping make the world a better place, when really we're hiding away in our gated communities flying the "we are in this together" flags from the safety of our lived realities—realities that let us change the channel or switch the outside world off altogether when things get too uncomfortable.</p>
<p>In a reality where multiple things can be true at once- yes, things can be shit, we can 100% be complicit in the bullshit happening in the world, but I also genuinely wish you a happy holiday break and hope you and your families get the rest and recharge needed to head into the new year- because you're going to need it.</p>
<p>2026 actions speak louder than words.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading. I'll be taking a break in January—back in February with our regularly scheduled programming of Uncommon Engineer optimism and wisdom.</p>
<p>ia manuia,</p>
<p>Ron.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>AI-Sovereignty-Governance</category>
            <category>tech-politics</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[AI Is a Conversation]]></title>
            <link>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/ai-is-a-conversation</link>
            <guid>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/ai-is-a-conversation</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Argues quality AI results depend on user communication skills exposing broader problem with collaborative thinking and perspective-taking. Essential reading for]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="AI Is a Conversation" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/ai-conversation-74efb515011856746fecfbbd91fbd0c4.png" width="2912" height="1632" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Talofa reader,</p>
<p>I remember one of my first AI-related engagements with one of my highly capable AWS Partners, a multi-national, multi-billion dollar company, highly resourced. It was early 2024, and I was delivering a workshop on GenAI. I was talking with one of the company tech leaders, and I was a little surprised at how they were thinking about AI—essentially, off-loading a good chunk of the problem decisions to the LLMs, and little to no emphasis on context details and scope going either way: to, from and back to the LLM.</p>
<p>We now know that "context" is king, apparent in the current surge of "context engineering" posts and videos—but it did baffle me a bit why this wasn't more understood in the early days.</p>
<p>But since that time of my first customer facing engagements, to now, I've had quite a few conversations, and my surprise in that initial engagement led me to poke at this apparent "gap" in AI understanding—and not in understanding "what does an LLM do" or "how an LLM works"—but in what you, the user, thinks is going on between you and the AI system you're interacting with.</p>
<p><strong>It's always a conversation</strong></p>
<p>This might sound asinine at this point in the AI hype cycle—but I really don't think people fully grasp what this means. It's a conversation. And comes with everything a conversation comes with. And I think if this isn't fully landing, to me, it calls into question not only what your understanding is of what a conversation is, but also if you're any good at having them.</p>
<p>So we should start right at the beginning—a conversation is between one or more people, or entities—I deliberately say "one or more" because talking to yourself is also a conversation.</p>
<p>Right off the bat, you now have multiple "points of view" to consider—no two people are exactly the same, and with that comes differences in understanding, definitions, experiences, levels of knowledge, levels of awareness and so on.</p>
<p>Let's call this first level of abstraction, multiple buckets of "data" or information. It's just a static snapshot of information, grouped per entity (person).</p>
<p>Now we introduce "movement"—how I think about the shift from scalar to vector. When the conversation starts moving—entities and their buckets in motion—we have to determine what exactly is driving and steering the conversation. What are the entities' instructions, motivations and incentives—because this is what will give us an idea of what directions the conversation moves in, what information from the buckets might be used and in what order of priority, and then the resulting trajectory of the conversation.</p>
<p>At this point, you will have an idea of where the conversation is going, why it's going that way, and potentially highlight what data might be missing from the conversation to have had it go in a direction you actually wanted it to go.</p>
<p><em>What's an example of this phenomenon?</em></p>
<p>Vibe coding yourself to an over-engineered, over-complicated, useless application that doesn't deliver what you wanted it to.</p>
<p>And why did it go wrong? How do I count the ways:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Jumped straight into "build" mode with no prior thinking, no discussion, nothing outside a vague idea of what you wanted to achieve—what you want to build, sure, but you don't actually know what you want to achieve.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Allowed too much of the design thinking to be done by the LLM. Now you're in its world, which vaguely resembles our current understanding of how humans think, but ultimately is orders of magnitude more basic and less capable than the human brain.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The incentives of the LLM are to "please its user"—what kind of goal is that? Do you know where that's going to take things, left unchecked?</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>I've seen Coursera courses made by big-time CEOs who have learned this concept, coaching executives on making the AI your "thought partner", and that concept is the collaborative element of AI, that the process is a two-way street that requires listening to understand what's coming back to you and adapting to things going back.</p>
<p>Other examples include:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Asking ChatGPT for business strategy advice, getting generic platitudes back, then declaring "AI is crap for business plans"—completely missing that you asked a nothing question and got a nothing answer back.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Copy-pasting increasingly complex prompts and code from the internet, wondering why you're getting inconsistent results, never stopping to think: "maybe I don't actually understand what I'm funnelling into the AI—how could I possibly know what to expect back?"</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>And I think the inability to see and understand not just this concept, but inherently, how deeply this is crucial to your interactions with AI, exposes something that was probably either hidden behind other factors in the workplace, or processes that allowed this gap to not be fully appreciated—</p>
<p>You suck at communication.</p>
<p>You don't know how to listen to understand, you don't know how to self-reflect, to empathise and to consider different points of view. The "other" in this case is the AI. You used to be able to fob it off on other people, and processes etc, but now it's just you and the tools.</p>
<p>AI isn't exposing a technical skills gap. It's exposing people who've never learned to think collaboratively, listen generatively, or hold space for differing perspectives. People who used to get cover through team dynamics where teammates picked up the slack, or managers who'd bark "harden up" or "find somewhere else to work" when they couldn't possibly admit to a leadership problem.</p>
<p>Now it's just you and the stochastic parrot who'd happily drive you both off a cliff if you asked. You've only got yourself to look at in the mirror and ask: "Do I actually know how to communicate well? Or am I a bit shit at it?"</p>
<p>I approach AI like it's doing its best impression of human thinking, and I'm doing my best impression of a human right alongside it. Whether that makes me better at this than most people, or just aware enough to see how shit we all are at it—I'll let you decide.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading,</p>
<p>Ron.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>AI-Sovereignty-Governance</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Re-Host. Re-Factor. Re-Up.]]></title>
            <link>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/re-host-re-factor-re-up</link>
            <guid>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/re-host-re-factor-re-up</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Newsletter relaunch on Beehiiv clarifying Uncommon Engineer's focus on technology power and insider Pasifika tech perspective. Essential reading for understandi]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Re-Host. Re-Factor. Re-Up." src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/rehost-refactor-f2696af10e05366df63a6ee2df4b4bc3.png" width="2048" height="2048" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Talofa reader,</p>
<p>I know it's been some time between posts, but thanks for making the move with me from Substack to Beehiiv.</p>
<p>Welcome to the new home<!-- -->:www<!-- -->.uncommonengineer.com</p>
<p>With the new location, it feels like a good time to get reacquainted—and to be clear about what<em>The Uncommon Engineer</em>actually is, because it might not be what you originally signed up for.</p>
<p>I write about technology, power and what it’s like being one of the few Pasifika at my level inside the tech industry. Sometimes it’s about AI and sovereignty. Sometimes it’s about hackers selling out. Sometimes it’s personal— shutting down failed projects or working through contradictions of living inside the very system I’m criticising.</p>
<p>This isn’t neutral tech coverage. It’s my perspective from inside “the machine”.</p>
<p><em>So, what makes me and my ideas different?</em></p>
<p>I’m Samoan, Tuvalu, Chinese. Son of a preacher. Second eldest of 5 brothers. Married, Father of a 2 year old. Twenty years in tech across multiple senior disciplines. Snr Solution Architect at Amazon. Former Professional MMA fighter. Former Touring musician across ANZ. Brazilian Jiu Jitsu black belt.Samoan mataiwith ape'a. Fourteen years sobriety in 2025. I've lived and travelled across ANZ, The Pacific, UK, Europe, Russia.</p>
<p>That’s some of the lenses I see the world through, so bear that in mind as you read through my writing.</p>
<p>If nothing else, you'll leave thinking about things a little bit differently.</p>
<p>You won't find tutorials here, or step-by-step guides on tech or careers (you can find that kind of writing on my blog athttps://ronamosa.io/).</p>
<p>What you<em>will</em>find: my thoughts on<strong>AI</strong>,<strong>Cloud</strong>,<strong>hacking</strong>, corporate culture, the tech industry, my Pasifika communities and their struggles, and the intersections of all of those things.</p>
<p>I’m not here to be controversial for the sake of being controversial.</p>
<p>I had a fellow leader in my community tell me he had recommended me to some Pasifika people looking for some AI help, and they said “not him”. Which I find funny, cos I don’t think I’ve said anything terribly controversial in my community, and it still rubbed someone the wrong way.</p>
<p>And that’s the point— you can’t please everyone all the time, and you’ll be lucky to please some people, any of the time.</p>
<p>So you may as well say your piece, be open to some good faith dialogue, and learn from the experience.</p>
<p>I will send one piece to your inbox, fortnightly, Sunday evenings NZT.</p>
<p>If that's not what you're looking for, no hard feelings—you can unsubscribe anytime below. But if you want to hear my thoughts from inside the machine— you’re in the right place.</p>
<p>Talk soon,</p>
<p>Ia manuia.</p>
<p>— Ron</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>AI-Sovereignty-Governance</category>
            <category>pasifika</category>
            <category>tech-politics</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Complexity Wall: My Half-Day Experiment with Spec-Driven Development (SDD)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/09/16/lessons-learned-the-complexity-wall</link>
            <guid>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/09/16/lessons-learned-the-complexity-wall</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[How a simple bias highlighter became a 96-task enterprise project in 4 hours. A practical lesson in over-engineering, spec-driven development pitfalls, and the value of starting embarrassingly simple.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="The Complexity Wall - Spec-Driven Development Experiment" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/complexity-wall-cover-300c47d965fe62cd37d6cbded585cadc.png" width="1456" height="816" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p><em>How a simple bias highlighter became a 96-task enterprise project in 4 hours</em></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="tldr">TL;DR<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/09/16/lessons-learned-the-complexity-wall#tldr" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to TL;DR" title="Direct link to TL;DR">​</a></h2>
<p>I spent a half-day (4-5 hours) experimenting with Spec-Driven Development using the spec-kit framework on GitHub. I gave it a simple project idea - a Chrome extension to highlight bias in news articles - but my overly complex project description led to a 96-task implementation plan that completely missed the point. The lesson: Even the input to SDD frameworks matters enormously.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-experiment-setup">The Experiment Setup<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/09/16/lessons-learned-the-complexity-wall#the-experiment-setup" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Experiment Setup" title="Direct link to The Experiment Setup">​</a></h2>
<p>I wanted to test Spec-Driven Development, specifically using <a href="https://github.com/specify-ai/spec-kit" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">spec-kit</a> integrated with Claude Code. The idea wasn't exactly simple: build a Chrome extension that highlights obviously biased language in news articles, but I had faith SDD would be able to handle it.</p>
<p>Instead of just building it with a light vibe coding session, I decided to feed this into the spec-kit framework to see what SDD would produce.</p>
<p><strong>My input description</strong> (this was my first mistake):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"This project is a Chrome extension that analyzes news articles and other web content to detect and reduce bias. The extension extracts the full text of an article, highlights loaded or emotional language directly in the page, and generates a side panel with structured analysis. It identifies factual claims, classifies them, and uses a language model to check those claims against external evidence from web search and fact-checking sources..."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I kept going, adding AI backends, performance requirements, privacy controls, and more. What should have been "highlight bias words" became a comprehensive news analysis platform description.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-spec-kit-generated">What Spec-Kit Generated<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/09/16/lessons-learned-the-complexity-wall#what-spec-kit-generated" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What Spec-Kit Generated" title="Direct link to What Spec-Kit Generated">​</a></h2>
<p>The framework took my verbose description and created:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>18 functional requirements</strong> (FR-001 through FR-018)</li>
<li><strong>6 detailed data models</strong> (ArticleContent, BiasHighlight, FactualClaim, etc.)</li>
<li><strong>8 API endpoints</strong> for different analysis functions</li>
<li><strong>96 numbered tasks</strong> organized into phases</li>
<li><strong>Performance targets</strong> (&lt;2s analysis, &lt;500ms highlighting)</li>
<li><strong>Multiple processing modes</strong> (local AI, cloud APIs)</li>
</ul>
<p>Looking at this output, any reasonable person would think this was a serious enterprise project- which would be fine if I was building a real product, but I was just trying to test SDD.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-implementation-reality-check">The Implementation Reality Check<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/09/16/lessons-learned-the-complexity-wall#the-implementation-reality-check" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Implementation Reality Check" title="Direct link to The Implementation Reality Check">​</a></h2>
<p>After half a day of following the generated spec with extensive "vibe-coding" (rapid, intuitive development), here's what I actually built:</p>
<p><strong>What Works:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>✅ Extracts text from web pages</li>
<li>✅ Finds basic patterns like "73%" and "$2.3 billion"</li>
<li>✅ Has a storage system</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>What Doesn't Work:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>❌ Buggy, basic bias detection</li>
<li>❌ No fact-checking</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>The harsh truth</strong>: I have a basic app that finds percentages in text, not a Chrome extension that detects bias.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-complexity-wall-in-action">The Complexity Wall in Action<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/09/16/lessons-learned-the-complexity-wall#the-complexity-wall-in-action" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Complexity Wall in Action" title="Direct link to The Complexity Wall in Action">​</a></h2>
<p>The most telling moment came during testing. I spent hours building increasingly specific regex patterns to satisfy test cases:</p>
<div class="language-typescript codeBlockContainer_Ckt0 theme-code-block" style="--prism-color:#d6deeb;--prism-background-color:#011627"><div class="codeBlockContent_QJqH"><pre tabindex="0" class="prism-code language-typescript codeBlock_bY9V thin-scrollbar" style="color:#d6deeb;background-color:#011627"><code class="codeBlockLines_e6Vv"><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token comment" style="color:rgb(99, 119, 119);font-style:italic">// Started simple</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">pattern</span><span class="token operator" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">:</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token regex regex-delimiter">/</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex char-set class-name" style="color:rgb(255, 203, 139)">\d</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex quantifier number" style="color:rgb(247, 140, 108)">+</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex">%</span><span class="token regex regex-delimiter">/</span><span class="token regex regex-flags">gi</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain" style="display:inline-block"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token comment" style="color:rgb(99, 119, 119);font-style:italic">// Became this monstrosity to pass tests</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">pattern</span><span class="token operator" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">:</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token regex regex-delimiter">/</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex anchor function" style="color:rgb(130, 170, 255)">\b</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex group punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">(</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex">current</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex alternation keyword" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">|</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex">currently</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex alternation keyword" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">|</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex">as of </span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex group punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">(</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex">today</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex alternation keyword" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">|</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex">now</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex alternation keyword" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">|</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex char-set class-name" style="color:rgb(255, 203, 139)">\d</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex quantifier number" style="color:rgb(247, 140, 108)">{4}</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex group punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">)</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex alternation keyword" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">|</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex">current</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex group punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">(</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex">ly</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex group punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">)</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex quantifier number" style="color:rgb(247, 140, 108)">?</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex group punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">)</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex char-set class-name" style="color:rgb(255, 203, 139)">\s</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex quantifier number" style="color:rgb(247, 140, 108)">+</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex char-class char-class-punctuation punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">[</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex char-class char-class-negation operator" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">^</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex char-class">.!?</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex char-class char-class-punctuation punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">]</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex quantifier number" style="color:rgb(247, 140, 108)">*</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex anchor function" style="color:rgb(130, 170, 255)">\b</span><span class="token regex regex-delimiter">/</span><span class="token regex regex-flags">gi</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain" style="display:inline-block"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token comment" style="color:rgb(99, 119, 119);font-style:italic">// And eventually this madness</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">{</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">  type</span><span class="token operator" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">:</span><span class="token plain"> ClaimType</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">.</span><span class="token constant" style="color:rgb(130, 170, 255)">STATISTICAL</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">,</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">  pattern</span><span class="token operator" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">:</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token regex regex-delimiter">/</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex">Water boils at </span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex char-set class-name" style="color:rgb(255, 203, 139)">\d</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex quantifier number" style="color:rgb(247, 140, 108)">+</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex">°C</span><span class="token regex regex-delimiter">/</span><span class="token regex regex-flags">gi</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">,</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">  priority</span><span class="token operator" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">:</span><span class="token plain"> ClaimPriority</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">.</span><span class="token constant" style="color:rgb(130, 170, 255)">HIGH</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">,</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">  description</span><span class="token operator" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">:</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token string" style="color:rgb(173, 219, 103)">'Temperature boiling point statements'</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">,</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">  examples</span><span class="token operator" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">:</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">[</span><span class="token string" style="color:rgb(173, 219, 103)">'Water boils at 100°C'</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">]</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">}</span><br></span></code></pre></div></div>
<p>I was adding patterns like "Water boils at 100°C" to pass tests instead of asking: <strong>"Would a real user care about detecting this?"</strong></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-specific-failure-points">The Specific Failure Points<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/09/16/lessons-learned-the-complexity-wall#the-specific-failure-points" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Specific Failure Points" title="Direct link to The Specific Failure Points">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="1-test-driven-anti-pattern">1. <strong>Test-Driven Anti-Pattern</strong><a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/09/16/lessons-learned-the-complexity-wall#1-test-driven-anti-pattern" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 1-test-driven-anti-pattern" title="Direct link to 1-test-driven-anti-pattern">​</a></h3>
<p>Instead of writing tests for user value, I wrote tests for specification compliance:</p>
<div class="language-typescript codeBlockContainer_Ckt0 theme-code-block" style="--prism-color:#d6deeb;--prism-background-color:#011627"><div class="codeBlockContent_QJqH"><pre tabindex="0" class="prism-code language-typescript codeBlock_bY9V thin-scrollbar" style="color:#d6deeb;background-color:#011627"><code class="codeBlockLines_e6Vv"><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token comment" style="color:rgb(99, 119, 119);font-style:italic">// Spec-driven test</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token function" style="color:rgb(130, 170, 255)">expect</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">(</span><span class="token plain">claimsResponse</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">.</span><span class="token plain">claims</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">.</span><span class="token plain">length</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">)</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">.</span><span class="token function" style="color:rgb(130, 170, 255)">toBeGreaterThan</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">(</span><span class="token number" style="color:rgb(247, 140, 108)">3</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">)</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token function" style="color:rgb(130, 170, 255)">expect</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">(</span><span class="token plain">temporalClaims</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">.</span><span class="token plain">length</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">)</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">.</span><span class="token function" style="color:rgb(130, 170, 255)">toBeGreaterThan</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">(</span><span class="token number" style="color:rgb(247, 140, 108)">0</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">)</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token function" style="color:rgb(130, 170, 255)">expect</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">(</span><span class="token plain">percentageClaims</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">.</span><span class="token plain">length</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">)</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">.</span><span class="token function" style="color:rgb(130, 170, 255)">toBeGreaterThan</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">(</span><span class="token number" style="color:rgb(247, 140, 108)">2</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">)</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain" style="display:inline-block"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token comment" style="color:rgb(99, 119, 119);font-style:italic">// User-driven test would be</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token function" style="color:rgb(130, 170, 255)">expect</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">(</span><span class="token plain">userCanIdentifyObviousBias</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">)</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">.</span><span class="token function" style="color:rgb(130, 170, 255)">toBe</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">(</span><span class="token boolean" style="color:rgb(255, 88, 116)">true</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">)</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">;</span><br></span></code></pre></div></div>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="2-premature-abstraction">2. <strong>Premature Abstraction</strong><a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/09/16/lessons-learned-the-complexity-wall#2-premature-abstraction" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 2-premature-abstraction" title="Direct link to 2-premature-abstraction">​</a></h3>
<p>The spec called for 6 services:</p>
<ul>
<li>ContentExtractor</li>
<li>BiasDetector</li>
<li>ClaimExtractor</li>
<li>ClaimVerifier</li>
<li>ObjectiveRewriter</li>
<li>StorageManager</li>
</ul>
<p>A working prototype needed exactly 1: "HighlightObviousBiasWords"</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="3-feature-explosion">3. <strong>Feature Explosion</strong><a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/09/16/lessons-learned-the-complexity-wall#3-feature-explosion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 3-feature-explosion" title="Direct link to 3-feature-explosion">​</a></h3>
<p>The original idea: "Highlight biased language"</p>
<p>The spec expanded to:</p>
<ul>
<li>Fact-checking against external databases</li>
<li>AI-powered claim verification with confidence scores</li>
<li>Objective article rewriting</li>
<li>Both local and cloud AI processing</li>
<li>Performance optimization and caching</li>
<li>Chrome extension manifest configuration</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="4-zero-user-validation">4. <strong>Zero User Validation</strong><a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/09/16/lessons-learned-the-complexity-wall#4-zero-user-validation" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 4-zero-user-validation" title="Direct link to 4-zero-user-validation">​</a></h3>
<p>96 tasks to implement features that no user ever requested. The spec assumed people wanted:</p>
<ul>
<li>Detailed confidence scores</li>
<li>Citation management</li>
<li>Bias radar visualizations</li>
<li>Multiple AI processing modes</li>
</ul>
<p>Maybe users just want obvious bias words highlighted in yellow. We'll never know because we never shipped anything testable.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-simplification-moment">The Simplification Moment<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/09/16/lessons-learned-the-complexity-wall#the-simplification-moment" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Simplification Moment" title="Direct link to The Simplification Moment">​</a></h2>
<p>The breakthrough came when I aggressively simplified the claim extractor from 50+ complex patterns to just 4:</p>
<div class="language-typescript codeBlockContainer_Ckt0 theme-code-block" style="--prism-color:#d6deeb;--prism-background-color:#011627"><div class="codeBlockContent_QJqH"><pre tabindex="0" class="prism-code language-typescript codeBlock_bY9V thin-scrollbar" style="color:#d6deeb;background-color:#011627"><code class="codeBlockLines_e6Vv"><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token comment" style="color:rgb(99, 119, 119);font-style:italic">// Before: 50+ patterns for every edge case</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token keyword" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">private</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token keyword" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">readonly</span><span class="token plain"> patterns</span><span class="token operator" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">:</span><span class="token plain"> ClaimPattern</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">[</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">]</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token operator" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">=</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">[</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token comment" style="color:rgb(99, 119, 119);font-style:italic">// 47 more patterns...</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">]</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain" style="display:inline-block"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token comment" style="color:rgb(99, 119, 119);font-style:italic">// After: 4 simple patterns that actually work</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token keyword" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">private</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token keyword" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">readonly</span><span class="token plain"> patterns</span><span class="token operator" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">:</span><span class="token plain"> ClaimPattern</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">[</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">]</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token operator" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">=</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">[</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">{</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">    type</span><span class="token operator" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">:</span><span class="token plain"> ClaimType</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">.</span><span class="token constant" style="color:rgb(130, 170, 255)">STATISTICAL</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">,</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">    pattern</span><span class="token operator" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">:</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token regex regex-delimiter">/</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex char-set class-name" style="color:rgb(255, 203, 139)">\d</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex quantifier number" style="color:rgb(247, 140, 108)">+</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex group punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">(</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex special-escape escape">\.</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex char-set class-name" style="color:rgb(255, 203, 139)">\d</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex quantifier number" style="color:rgb(247, 140, 108)">+</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex group punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">)</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex quantifier number" style="color:rgb(247, 140, 108)">?</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex">%</span><span class="token regex regex-delimiter">/</span><span class="token regex regex-flags">gi</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">,</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">    description</span><span class="token operator" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">:</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token string" style="color:rgb(173, 219, 103)">'Percentage values'</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">}</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">,</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">{</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">    type</span><span class="token operator" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">:</span><span class="token plain"> ClaimType</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">.</span><span class="token constant" style="color:rgb(130, 170, 255)">STATISTICAL</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">,</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">    pattern</span><span class="token operator" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">:</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token regex regex-delimiter">/</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex special-escape escape">\$</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex char-set class-name" style="color:rgb(255, 203, 139)">\d</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex quantifier number" style="color:rgb(247, 140, 108)">+</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex group punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">(</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex special-escape escape">\.</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex char-set class-name" style="color:rgb(255, 203, 139)">\d</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex quantifier number" style="color:rgb(247, 140, 108)">+</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex group punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">)</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex quantifier number" style="color:rgb(247, 140, 108)">?</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex char-set class-name" style="color:rgb(255, 203, 139)">\s</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex quantifier number" style="color:rgb(247, 140, 108)">*</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex group punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">(</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex">million</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex alternation keyword" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">|</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex">billion</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex group punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">)</span><span class="token regex regex-delimiter">/</span><span class="token regex regex-flags">gi</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">,</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">    description</span><span class="token operator" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">:</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token string" style="color:rgb(173, 219, 103)">'Currency amounts'</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">}</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">,</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">{</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">    type</span><span class="token operator" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">:</span><span class="token plain"> ClaimType</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">.</span><span class="token constant" style="color:rgb(130, 170, 255)">TEMPORAL</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">,</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">    pattern</span><span class="token operator" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">:</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token regex regex-delimiter">/</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex anchor function" style="color:rgb(130, 170, 255)">\b</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex group punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">(</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex">January</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex alternation keyword" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">|</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex">February</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex alternation keyword" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">|</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex">March</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex alternation keyword" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">|</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex">April</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex alternation keyword" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">|</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex">May</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex alternation keyword" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">|</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex">June</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex alternation keyword" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">|</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex">July</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex alternation keyword" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">|</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex">August</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex alternation keyword" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">|</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex">September</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex alternation keyword" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">|</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex">October</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex alternation keyword" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">|</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex">November</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex alternation keyword" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">|</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex">December</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex group punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">)</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex char-set class-name" style="color:rgb(255, 203, 139)">\s</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex quantifier number" style="color:rgb(247, 140, 108)">+</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex char-set class-name" style="color:rgb(255, 203, 139)">\d</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex quantifier number" style="color:rgb(247, 140, 108)">{4}</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex anchor function" style="color:rgb(130, 170, 255)">\b</span><span class="token regex regex-delimiter">/</span><span class="token regex regex-flags">gi</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">,</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">    description</span><span class="token operator" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">:</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token string" style="color:rgb(173, 219, 103)">'Month and year references'</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">}</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">,</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">{</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">    type</span><span class="token operator" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">:</span><span class="token plain"> ClaimType</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">.</span><span class="token constant" style="color:rgb(130, 170, 255)">TEMPORAL</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">,</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">    pattern</span><span class="token operator" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">:</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token regex regex-delimiter">/</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex anchor function" style="color:rgb(130, 170, 255)">\b</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex">202</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex char-set class-name" style="color:rgb(255, 203, 139)">\d</span><span class="token regex regex-source language-regex anchor function" style="color:rgb(130, 170, 255)">\b</span><span class="token regex regex-delimiter">/</span><span class="token regex regex-flags">gi</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">,</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">    description</span><span class="token operator" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">:</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token string" style="color:rgb(173, 219, 103)">'Recent years'</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">}</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">]</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">;</span><br></span></code></pre></div></div>
<p>Immediately, 6 out of 8 tests passed. The complex patterns were solving imaginary problems.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-i-should-have-done">What I Should Have Done<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/09/16/lessons-learned-the-complexity-wall#what-i-should-have-done" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What I Should Have Done" title="Direct link to What I Should Have Done">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Week 1: Stupid Simple Prototype</strong></p>
<div class="language-javascript codeBlockContainer_Ckt0 theme-code-block" style="--prism-color:#d6deeb;--prism-background-color:#011627"><div class="codeBlockContent_QJqH"><pre tabindex="0" class="prism-code language-javascript codeBlock_bY9V thin-scrollbar" style="color:#d6deeb;background-color:#011627"><code class="codeBlockLines_e6Vv"><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token comment" style="color:rgb(99, 119, 119);font-style:italic">// 20 lines of code</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token keyword" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">const</span><span class="token plain"> biasWords </span><span class="token operator" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">=</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">[</span><span class="token string" style="color:rgb(173, 219, 103)">'devastating'</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">,</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token string" style="color:rgb(173, 219, 103)">'shocking'</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">,</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token string" style="color:rgb(173, 219, 103)">'outrageous'</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">,</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token string" style="color:rgb(173, 219, 103)">'slam'</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">]</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token keyword" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">const</span><span class="token plain"> textNodes </span><span class="token operator" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">=</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token dom variable" style="color:rgb(214, 222, 235)">document</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">.</span><span class="token method function property-access" style="color:rgb(130, 170, 255)">querySelectorAll</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">(</span><span class="token string" style="color:rgb(173, 219, 103)">'p'</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">)</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">textNodes</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">.</span><span class="token method function property-access" style="color:rgb(130, 170, 255)">forEach</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">(</span><span class="token parameter">node</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token arrow operator" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">=&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">{</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">  biasWords</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">.</span><span class="token method function property-access" style="color:rgb(130, 170, 255)">forEach</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">(</span><span class="token parameter">word</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token arrow operator" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">=&gt;</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">{</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token keyword control-flow" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">if</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">(</span><span class="token plain">node</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">.</span><span class="token property-access">textContent</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">.</span><span class="token method function property-access" style="color:rgb(130, 170, 255)">includes</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">(</span><span class="token plain">word</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">)</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">)</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">{</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">      node</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">.</span><span class="token property-access">innerHTML</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token operator" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">=</span><span class="token plain"> node</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">.</span><span class="token property-access">innerHTML</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">.</span><span class="token method function property-access" style="color:rgb(130, 170, 255)">replace</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">(</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">        </span><span class="token keyword" style="color:rgb(127, 219, 202)">new</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token class-name" style="color:rgb(255, 203, 139)">RegExp</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">(</span><span class="token plain">word</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">,</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token string" style="color:rgb(173, 219, 103)">'gi'</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">)</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">,</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">        </span><span class="token template-string template-punctuation string" style="color:rgb(173, 219, 103)">`</span><span class="token template-string string" style="color:rgb(173, 219, 103)">&lt;mark style="background: yellow"&gt;</span><span class="token template-string interpolation interpolation-punctuation punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">${</span><span class="token template-string interpolation">word</span><span class="token template-string interpolation interpolation-punctuation punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">}</span><span class="token template-string string" style="color:rgb(173, 219, 103)">&lt;/mark&gt;</span><span class="token template-string template-punctuation string" style="color:rgb(173, 219, 103)">`</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">      </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">)</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">}</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">}</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">)</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#d6deeb"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">}</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">)</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(199, 146, 234)">;</span><br></span></code></pre></div></div>
<p>Ship this. See if anyone uses it. Get feedback.</p>
<p><strong>Week 2-4: Iterate Based on Feedback</strong>
Only add complexity that users actually request.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-lessons">The Lessons<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/09/16/lessons-learned-the-complexity-wall#the-lessons" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Lessons" title="Direct link to The Lessons">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="1-specifications-are-procrastination">1. <strong>Specifications Are Procrastination</strong><a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/09/16/lessons-learned-the-complexity-wall#1-specifications-are-procrastination" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 1-specifications-are-procrastination" title="Direct link to 1-specifications-are-procrastination">​</a></h3>
<p>Writing detailed specs feels productive but delays the only thing that matters: user feedback.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="2-complexity-walls-are-real">2. <strong>Complexity Walls Are Real</strong><a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/09/16/lessons-learned-the-complexity-wall#2-complexity-walls-are-real" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 2-complexity-walls-are-real" title="Direct link to 2-complexity-walls-are-real">​</a></h3>
<p>There's a point where additional features make it harder, not easier, to ship something useful.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="3-test-what-users-care-about">3. <strong>Test What Users Care About</strong><a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/09/16/lessons-learned-the-complexity-wall#3-test-what-users-care-about" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 3-test-what-users-care-about" title="Direct link to 3-test-what-users-care-about">​</a></h3>
<p>Testing specification compliance is not the same as testing user value.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="4-start-embarrassingly-simple">4. <strong>Start Embarrassingly Simple</strong><a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/09/16/lessons-learned-the-complexity-wall#4-start-embarrassingly-simple" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 4-start-embarrassingly-simple" title="Direct link to 4-start-embarrassingly-simple">​</a></h3>
<p>A working prototype that highlights 10 bias words is infinitely more valuable than a sophisticated system that analyzes confidence scores of extracted temporal claims.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="5-frameworks-encourage-over-engineering">5. <strong>Frameworks Encourage Over-Engineering</strong><a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/09/16/lessons-learned-the-complexity-wall#5-frameworks-encourage-over-engineering" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 5-frameworks-encourage-over-engineering" title="Direct link to 5-frameworks-encourage-over-engineering">​</a></h3>
<p>The "proper" way to build software often prevents you from building software at all.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-real-cost">The Real Cost<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/09/16/lessons-learned-the-complexity-wall#the-real-cost" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Real Cost" title="Direct link to The Real Cost">​</a></h2>
<p>Time spent: <strong>1 weeks</strong>
Lines of code written: <strong>~3,000</strong>
Chrome extensions shipped: <strong>0</strong>
User feedback collected: <strong>0</strong>
Problems solved: <strong>0</strong></p>
<p>A 20-line bias word highlighter would have solved an actual problem and been in users' hands on day 1.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="whats-next">What's Next<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/09/16/lessons-learned-the-complexity-wall#whats-next" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What's Next" title="Direct link to What's Next">​</a></h2>
<p>I've already scrapped this down to MVP level and rebuliding from scratch, and got a working prototype ready to publish and get user feedback.</p>
<p>If people use it, iterate. If they don't, I'll know in days instead of months.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/09/16/lessons-learned-the-complexity-wall#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h2>
<p>Detailed specifications create an illusion of progress while preventing actual progress. The road to user value is paved with working prototypes, not comprehensive requirements documents.</p>
<hr>
<div class="theme-admonition theme-admonition-info admonition_xJq3 alert alert--info"><div class="admonitionHeading_Gvgb"><span class="admonitionIcon_Rf37"><svg viewBox="0 0 14 16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7 2.3c3.14 0 5.7 2.56 5.7 5.7s-2.56 5.7-5.7 5.7A5.71 5.71 0 0 1 1.3 8c0-3.14 2.56-5.7 5.7-5.7zM7 1C3.14 1 0 4.14 0 8s3.14 7 7 7 7-3.14 7-7-3.14-7-7-7zm1 3H6v5h2V4zm0 6H6v2h2v-2z"></path></svg></span>🤖 AI Collaboration</div><div class="admonitionContent_BuS1"><p>This post was generated from a real debugging session with my AI assistant. All the steps, attempts, results, and challenges described here came from actual hands-on experimentation with the spec-kit framework. At the end of the session, I asked my AI assistant to summarize our entire conversation and the project experience into this blog post, which I then edited and published. The insights and lessons learned are from real experience, not hypothetical scenarios.</p></div></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>spec-driven-development</category>
            <category>software-engineering</category>
            <category>mvp</category>
            <category>prototyping</category>
            <category>complexity</category>
            <category>lessons-learned</category>
            <category>chrome-extension</category>
            <category>development-process</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Making a move...]]></title>
            <link>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/making-a-move</link>
            <guid>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/making-a-move</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Announcement moving newsletter off Substack to more ethical platform while reflecting on hyper-focus imbalance and pe'a journey. Essential reading for understan]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Making a move..." src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/making-a-move-43b656d735ea42a785260883faa94767.png" width="2688" height="1792" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Talofa reader,</p>
<p>I often don’t appreciate that there’s a couple of 100 people still subscribed to this newsletter.</p>
<p>At one point, before I turned it off, several of you were paying subscribers. In a world that sees “going viral” and having a million followers as a sign of success, we often don’t see the forest for the trees- a couple of hundred people, who deliberately signed up and look at and read my writing, is still a couple of hundred people- and that is a small miracle to be quite honest, because who am I?</p>
<p>I’m not a public figure, I’ve done a few things in public, but this is still an amazing stat, when I step back and think about it.</p>
<p>So, in that spirit I am truly grateful you’re here, you get these emails and you have a read of what’s on my mind at any one time these posts come through.</p>
<p>I appreciate you haven’t seen or heard much from me in the last… several months? And that’s definitely not for a lack of thoughts or things to say LOL. It’s just been a bit of a weird (and wonderful) time for me personally, professionally, spiritually etc.</p>
<p>Sometimes I’ll write through it, and I think it shows in my writing, but this time I chose to just stop- have a think about the world, look around and see if I could still see everything around me, not just the thing I’m currently hyper-focused on, cos often when that’s the case, everything else around me is blurry.</p>
<p>I never thought that was an issue before, I’m usually hyper focused digging into some new tech, or social issue, and I like going deep. But when that’s applied to anything and everything, the world starts getting really out of balance for me.</p>
<p>So, just stopping- having a look around, and if I’m not feeling it, I’ll just try to do something else like go to the gym, or watch a show and try to turn my brain off.</p>
<p>Then I remembered a lot of what helped turn my brain off, or at least settle it down, was writing…</p>
<p>So there’s been this weird loop of “I’m too hyper-focused, so I shouldn’t write anything, I’ll do something else to settle it down, that turns out to be very temporary, now I’m too hyper-focused, so I shouldn’t…”</p>
<p>That’s the weird<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/making-a-move#footnote-1">1</a>.</p>
<p>The wonderful is (and I will do a proper post and share of it at some stage) getting myPe’a. I took some time off in July (almost a month), to receive this and heal up before getting back to work this month.</p>
<p>Ok, just remembering I didn’t come here to give y’all an update on life in general, but that I’m going to be moving off substack.</p>
<p>I’ve thought about it for a while for variousreasons, and also wanted something that was just email based.</p>
<p>I still have plenty of thoughts and things I want to write about, and looking to make a fresh start on a different, more ethical platform (sure, what constitutes ethical these days, right?), but also, this place has turned into a hyper social media platform and I kinda just want to step off to the side somewhere and keep writing.</p>
<p>So I thought I’d just get in touch, say hi, hope you’ve been well, I’m moving and you’ll get another email from me soon (you shouldn’t have to do anything, the tech these days makes everything transferable to the next).</p>
<p>talk soon, ia manuia,</p>
<p>Ron.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>AI-Systems-Infrastructure</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The AI Resistance]]></title>
            <link>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/the-ai-resistance</link>
            <guid>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/the-ai-resistance</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Critiques anti-AI arguments showing AI unlike NFT scams has real value while defending against strawman comparisons. Essential reading for understanding this cr]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="The AI Resistance" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/ai-resistance-7b62e7c8749b8fd0c8c7a7debb1076d5.png" width="2912" height="1632" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Talofa reader,</p>
<p>I guess the first thing I should say about "AI" as a concept, an idea and a thing that's taken over the world as we know it, is- I'm not pro AI.</p>
<p>I'm not anti AI either- I feel like those labels immediately put people in the "extremes" of any argument and discussion.</p>
<p>Let's talk about how I see, and hear the argument about AI that I often see online.</p>
<p>I obviously lean "left" in many respects, despite my capitalist veneer, and "mercenary for hire" rhetoric around tech careers and navigating the corporate environment.</p>
<p>Which means many folks I socialise with, offline and on, will have views you can expect from that leaning.</p>
<p>Nothing wrong with it.</p>
<p>I can totally see where they're coming from.</p>
<p>However, it does mean, at such point that their beliefs come into contact with a reality that doesn't play well with them, things start to come apart.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-ai-is-a-scam-argument">The "AI Is a Scam" Argument<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/the-ai-resistance#the-ai-is-a-scam-argument" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The &quot;AI Is a Scam&quot; Argument" title="Direct link to The &quot;AI Is a Scam&quot; Argument">​</a></h2>
<p>Let's run through the argument, and discuss the ideas and challenges this presents, along the way.</p>
<p><em>“AI Is a Scam, and Has No Value.”</em></p>
<p>Now, I'm super empathetic to this statement because we lived through NFT's and of course still dealing with Crypto, Blockchain and Web3.</p>
<p>I get it, we have definitely been scammed before.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="comparing-ai-to-nfts-not-the-same">Comparing AI to NFTs: Not the Same<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/the-ai-resistance#comparing-ai-to-nfts-not-the-same" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Comparing AI to NFTs: Not the Same" title="Direct link to Comparing AI to NFTs: Not the Same">​</a></h2>
<p>But AI is not NFT's aka the literal poster child for "tech that has zero value".</p>
<p>How so?</p>
<p>Let's talk about NFTs- what was the value proposition or value exchange? You get a bored Ape image, that you exchange real money for, to be given an address in cyberspace, with a "claim" to that Ape.</p>
<p>Seriously.</p>
<p>Seriously, are you reading that sentence the way I am, while writing it?</p>
<p>It's in-sane!</p>
<p>The value of these things were all in the perception of it, like stocks and futures trading- pure speculation. It was something off into the future that you bet money would still be valuable when you got to that future<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/the-ai-resistance#footnote-1">1</a>.</p>
<p>NFT's were not tied to anything of value in the real world. Unless, of course, you count your hopes and dreams of a libertarian society as the real world assets this scam was connected to. And like pyramid schemes, aka multi-level marketing programmes, this scam needed<em><strong>people</strong></em>- droves of people to participate in the grift in order to see "value" in the system.</p>
<p>This mainly came in the form of the masses' money being funnelled to the "early adopters" via rug pull.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-evidence-debate">The Evidence Debate<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/the-ai-resistance#the-evidence-debate" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Evidence Debate" title="Direct link to The Evidence Debate">​</a></h2>
<p>To make this claim about AI feels somewhat disingenuous to me.</p>
<p>Especially now, when we're 2 years post ChatGPT release, with all the flurry of research, development activity, progress and market signalling.</p>
<p>I've seen those against AI hold up research to show AI doesn't do a thing well, or make a mistake a human wouldn't, or hasn't and will never deliver AGI.</p>
<p>Sure, I get that.</p>
<p>But you can also find research that shows the opposite.</p>
<p>That AI is helping, and improving outcomes- even if it's not where the marketers and the AI grifters have lead us to believe the benefits are coming from.</p>
<p>Evidence-based thinking is a tricky aspect of today's world.</p>
<p>We've lost trust in established institutions founded on science and evidence ~ and rightly so for various organisations for various reasons. We are living in a white supremacist world after all. Do we really think all these incumbent legacy institutions were established with the good of all humanity in mind?</p>
<p>Let's not be naive.</p>
<p>Some deserved to lose their trusted status. Some deserved to no longer be held up as sources of truth.</p>
<p>So, I get that.</p>
<p>But that doesn't mean evidence, scientific methods, research and the pursuit of knowledge, meaning and truth, don't exist anymore- they are more valuable than ever given the day and age we live in.</p>
<p>On one hand, the research that says ‘AI is a hallucinating, confidently incorrect stochastic parrot’.</p>
<p>True, but with nuance.</p>
<p>We don't take it all at face value, despite what major research names may be on the papers. The same way we don't believe everything OpenAI says about… well, about anything really. We listen, we read, we do our best to verify the claims. And if you're doing that to both sides of the argument, I would challenge the view that AI adds<em>no</em>value to anyone using it.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-value-question">The Value Question<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/the-ai-resistance#the-value-question" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Value Question" title="Direct link to The Value Question">​</a></h2>
<p>To say AI has "no value" is, to me, to devalue the experiences of those who have managed to utilise the capability the technology has been able to provide.</p>
<p>But AI… yeah, AI burns mad resources, AI does not do everything the grifters and the marketers promise.</p>
<p>AI is not a<em><strong>lot</strong></em>of things, but to say it's "nothing"?</p>
<p>I can’t take the position seriously.</p>
<p>I’m not making a moral judgement on the absolute value of AI, taking into consideration all things that are important to everyone. No.</p>
<p>I’m just asking, was this technology able to help you in a way that you weren’t able to be helped, before?</p>
<p>Making the judgement whether something is adding<em>value</em>somewhere is to understand something's struggle, aspirations, fears and needs. Saying AI is adding nothing to all peoples everywhere, is in my opinion, hubris on a massive scale.</p>
<p>If it adds no value to<em><strong>you</strong></em>, okay, but to dictate to everyone what value it holds to them, is a dangerous precedent that quickly moves to ignorance and then stubbornness.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="real-world-benefits">Real-World Benefits<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/the-ai-resistance#real-world-benefits" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Real-World Benefits" title="Direct link to Real-World Benefits">​</a></h2>
<p>Has AI helped you in any way?</p>
<p>I was told that whatever help I got from AI, was only perceived, was not real, that it was all wrong and a hallucination.</p>
<p>Did it help you understand a concept you weren't quite sure how to articulate, but was able to converse your way to an understanding with a chatbot?</p>
<p>Ok.</p>
<p>Did it help you build a small app or website? Did it make the experience easier than finding and reading the right tutorial for you? Was it more interactive than watching a video of someone else's setup getting it to work?</p>
<p>Ok.</p>
<p>Were you able to have conversations with a likeness trained on texts and studies? Studies that you might never have the opportunity to read otherwise? Did you glean some insight or knowledge from that conversation, in your own time and space?</p>
<p>Ok.</p>
<p>I can’t speak for anyone else’s experience, I can only speak from mine.</p>
<p>I am someone who uses AI on a daily basis for text, code, images and it has scaled my capacity and capability massively. There is no way I would be able to do the things I'm doing now, without it.</p>
<p>Do I need to check my work?</p>
<p>Of course.</p>
<p>Am I sure this code is bullet proof?</p>
<p>Of course not, but I know how to check, and I know enough to ensure and care about making bulletproof code.</p>
<p>But I’m not going to sit here and act like I haven’t worked with human beings over the last 20 years in tech who haven’t made some horrendous errors in coding, security and operations.</p>
<p>What about text summaries? Same deal, how do I know any human knows everything about everything and is always right? I don't, but how do I get the best out of any expert? I talk, I push, I query, I challenge.</p>
<p>The<em>conversation</em>is what's of value to me, this is not zero-shot copy and paste.</p>
<p>If you were this person before—not checking your work after reading things online and submitting it without filtering it through your own brain—then this is no different.</p>
<p>It just makes it faster for you to produce more slop that looks like everyone else’ slop.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="there-are-definitely-problems-in-ai">There Are Definitely Problems, in AI<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/the-ai-resistance#there-are-definitely-problems-in-ai" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to There Are Definitely Problems, in AI" title="Direct link to There Are Definitely Problems, in AI">​</a></h2>
<p>Yes, there are problems.</p>
<p>No-one (well, I'm not) is denying there are issues with the current AI marketplace.</p>
<p>It's full of grift, sustainability issues, bias and toxicity, labour displacement, intellectual property theft, labour displacement, etc.</p>
<p>These are rightfully concerning, and will have a massive effect on society. This is especially true given how quickly the technology is being adopted. Much of this adoption is driven by sales and marketing hype, fear-based arguments for regulatory control, or simple fear of missing out.</p>
<p>There’s folks, even in the Pasifika circles, promoting masterclasses in AI, with no AI background or professional experience- how are we to take these things seriously?</p>
<p>Yes, Sam Altman talks a bunch of shit- "AGI this" and "AGI that" since ChatGPT launched, and we're still on GPT4. I'm not saying developing AI models is easy by any stretch of the imagination, but good lord in heaven STFU with the marketing hype!</p>
<p>But what I am surprised by is that those same folks are reporting that enterprises are finding it difficult to get real ROI from their AI investments. They've commented on the dissatisfaction between what they were told AI could do and what it's actually capable of doing for their business.</p>
<p>No shit, Sherlock- did you hype-market spectators think for a second that this wasn't going to turn out badly? When hype meets reality, did you think there was going to be a happy customer at the end of that story?!</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="moving-forward">Moving Forward<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/the-ai-resistance#moving-forward" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Moving Forward" title="Direct link to Moving Forward">​</a></h2>
<p>So yes, there's bullshit-galore in the market. There are AI solutions that are not ready for prime-time being rolled out in education and law enforcement. And people are definitely going to have a bad time.</p>
<p>You can have your value-based views on anything you want. But we don't manoeuvre this world alone - as much as we want or try to. We exist within systems and ecosystems of interconnected people, resources and realities.</p>
<p>But abstaining from the tech, in my view, is not the move.</p>
<p>Unless, of course, you have the majority of the workforce worldwide signed up to join you en-masse? Because if you have that, I'm down for it.</p>
<p>That would actually do something.</p>
<p>My take? The faction that is able to wield this technology, for gain or for survival, gets to hang around. History has shown the folks who abstain from the technology of the time don't usually make it out of that era.</p>
<p>Is that really what you're choosing?</p>
<p>Thanks for reading,</p>
<p>Ron.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>AI-Security-Exploitation</category>
            <category>hacker-culture</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[To Live and Die in the Simulation]]></title>
            <link>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/to-live-die-in-simulation</link>
            <guid>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/to-live-die-in-simulation</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Examines living in simulated normalcy while real world suffers documenting contradiction between everyday routine and global catastrophe. Essential reading for ]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="To Live and Die in the Simulation" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/live-and-die-simulation-09f8d0726d184ab8ee6bcd835db9d6b6.png" width="1456" height="816" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Talofa Reader,</p>
<p>We live in a simulation.</p>
<p>Or at least that's what it feels like right now.</p>
<p>But what's being simulated is living a normal life, with its ups and downs, in a world that "has its problems" but is otherwise unproblematic- apparently.</p>
<p>And it's a simulation because outside of this "bubble" or "delusion" a lot of very bad things are going on in the world.</p>
<p>That's the preface and pretext of this piece.</p>
<p><em>[[send tweet]]</em></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-reality-beyond-the-bubble">The Reality Beyond the Bubble<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/to-live-die-in-simulation#the-reality-beyond-the-bubble" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Reality Beyond the Bubble" title="Direct link to The Reality Beyond the Bubble">​</a></h2>
<p>Why?</p>
<p><em>Why are we talking about the world, right now?</em></p>
<p>Because I sit down to write something, in amongst the many things I have going on in life, and to sit here and think about everything in the context of the "container" it exists in, I'm suddenly confronted by the reality of the insanity.</p>
<p>Now, obviously a lot of us, myself included, can be given to hyperbole. We call everything "crazy," "insane" or "unbelievable" when really, we have short memories. Even if a slightly older version of the same thing has happened before—even if unacceptable and bad (which isn't being litigated here)—it has happened enough times to not be as surprising. Not as 'unbelievable' as we hope it is. We imply it's totally different from what usually happens, but is it?</p>
<p>But if the horror happens often and consistently enough, what does it say about where we are now? A genocide like the one in Gaza is happening, and has been happening for over a year. The entire western system complete with "international law &amp; order" has been seen to be the farce that it is. We have the Elon and Trump clown show, complete with Grifter coins and the Department of Getting Even.</p>
<p>This forms the background to everything we're living through right now.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="my-world-vs-reality">My World vs. Reality<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/to-live-die-in-simulation#my-world-vs-reality" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to My World vs. Reality" title="Direct link to My World vs. Reality">​</a></h2>
<p>I work in a Big Tech company, and watching other big tech companies, riding abreast these massive waves of economic and social disharmony and change. Somewhat<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/to-live-die-in-simulation#footnote-1">1</a>insulated from the uglier side of what I'm constantly reading, and seeing in the news. Cost of living crisis, unemployment and homelessness increasing, businesses closing, the economy in a shambles and a NZ government ruthlessly and relentlessly slashing public services readying them for privatisation.</p>
<p>All the while, vilifying the victims of a legacy and history of malice and misfortune, ethnic and other minorities.</p>
<p>The usual targets.</p>
<p>There's just layers, and layers of this shit from international, to regional, Pacific, Australia and finally local here in New Zealand.</p>
<p>You'd be forgiven for thinking this rant was another one of my*"the world sucks, everything's burning but f**k it, let it burn, it all deserves to go to hell anyway"*rants.</p>
<p>And you'd be mostly right - that's sort of my default initial setting when faced with these facts.</p>
<h1>The Catharsis in Writing</h1>
<p>But this, out of the blue newsletter, which I'm sure folks are wondering which thing they signed up for now, is another semi-update of where life is right now for me, and finding that using this writing outlet to just - dump thoughts, edit and publish - is very…</p>
<p><em>cathartic</em>.</p>
<p><em>Is that what the Uncommon Engineer newsletter has become?</em></p>
<p>Well, sort of, yeah.</p>
<p>When I wanted to separate out the more "technical" things, into deep dives and commentary on things happening in the industry, the LinkedIn page made sense. It was essentially a way to "showcase" that information there<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/to-live-die-in-simulation#footnote-2">2</a>. The newsletter, on the other hand, was going to be the social commentary. I have about 30 drafts on different topics. They range from the scourge of middle management to being pigeon-holed by multiple dimensions all in the same, single user entity.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-makes-you-tick">What Makes You Tick?<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/to-live-die-in-simulation#what-makes-you-tick" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What Makes You Tick?" title="Direct link to What Makes You Tick?">​</a></h2>
<p>But then I re-discovered things that made me happier than writing down my weird and wacky takes, like building and making tech things.</p>
<p>Some for profit, most for just scratching the itch of just fucking around with a technology or platform or device to see what it can and can't do.</p>
<p>This doesn't need an audience - it has one already.</p>
<p>Me.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-dilemma">The Dilemma.<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/to-live-die-in-simulation#the-dilemma" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Dilemma." title="Direct link to The Dilemma.">​</a></h2>
<p>And therein lies my dilemma, to choose between a thing that I love and that might not make me a living wage, and a thing that I'm good at that's paying everything off and more.</p>
<p>“Do both”, I hear people say.</p>
<p>I have.</p>
<p>For years, I've done things alongside my tech career - professional drummer, cage fighter, community charity founder, motorcycle group "patched" member<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/to-live-die-in-simulation#footnote-3">3</a>, Brazilian Jujitsu black belt, and more.</p>
<p>I know people have hobbies and their main job, but as you can see my hobbies aren't part-time commitment level things. They usually need full-time commitment time investments. That's how you burn evenings, early hours, and weekends, for years. All to live this "do both" philosophy.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="new-purpose">New Purpose?<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/to-live-die-in-simulation#new-purpose" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to New Purpose?" title="Direct link to New Purpose?">​</a></h2>
<p>Where was I?</p>
<p>Oh yeah, this newsletter.</p>
<p>I first started it to see if I could make it a "thing". I knew it would be hard, I've done these things before, the goal was to make it something that I could lean on in the future, brand recognition or finances-wise. It would earn money eventually, or open opportunities.</p>
<p>But as much as I'm a writer, or enjoy writing<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/to-live-die-in-simulation#footnote-4">4</a>, I'm hard to narrow things down to a single-focus. Even though I know, and already experienced that I do my best work when I'm single-focused.</p>
<p>Sometimes the stars will align<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/to-live-die-in-simulation#footnote-5">5</a>, I'll focus, and I get some great outcomes. My life has been a series of alignment challenges, level unpredictable.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-way-forward">The Way Forward<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/to-live-die-in-simulation#the-way-forward" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Way Forward" title="Direct link to The Way Forward">​</a></h2>
<p>I'm working on some things now, and for better or worse, I may have to shut down some things that I was keen on before - I was thinking this newsletter, but then… what if I just keep writing stuff?</p>
<p>Now - I read a lot of other writers' stuff, journalists and folks who not only do writing for a living, but it's really their thing.</p>
<p>So I know that's not what's on offer here with my writing lol.</p>
<p>And maybe the pressure to either be all things to everyone, or even be something to someone, anyone, is alleviated when I can just write when I find the space, or conviction to make a thought and writing.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-beginning-is-the-end-is-the">The Beginning Is the End, Is The…<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/to-live-die-in-simulation#the-beginning-is-the-end-is-the" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Beginning Is the End, Is The…" title="Direct link to The Beginning Is the End, Is The…">​</a></h2>
<p>That's the madness that surrounds my inner world, juxtaposed against the madness of the outside world, and you and I carry on, brushing our teeth and taking the rubbish out on Weds, like everything's normal.</p>
<p>Like sure "things can be a bit shit, but that's life, right?" type normal, but it really isn't.</p>
<p>It's a simulation.</p>
<p>thanks for reading,</p>
<p>Ron.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>AI-Sovereignty-Governance</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Part 4: The Anatomy of AI Agents - Practical Security Implications]]></title>
            <link>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/03/04/agentic-ai-part-4</link>
            <guid>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/03/04/agentic-ai-part-4</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Explore practical security implications of AI agent vulnerabilities and learn about defense strategies, security principles, and approaches for protecting against agent-related threats in enterprise environments.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Practical AI Agent Security Implications and Defense Strategies" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/agentic-ai-part4-cover-a3b1ffbd87e6ea0bba223eeb1cdbc6c5.png" width="1232" height="693" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>In <a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/25/agentic-ai-part-3">Part 3</a>, we explored the core components of AI agents—the Brain, Perception, and Action modules—and the specific security vulnerabilities each introduces. Now, let's examine how these vulnerabilities create practical security challenges and discuss approaches for mitigating these risks.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="practical-security-implications">Practical Security Implications<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/03/04/agentic-ai-part-4#practical-security-implications" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Practical Security Implications" title="Direct link to Practical Security Implications">​</a></h2>
<p>Understanding individual component vulnerabilities is important, but the real security challenge emerges when we consider how these vulnerabilities interact in practice.</p>
<p>The interconnected nature of AI agent components creates a security challenge greater than the sum of its parts. Vulnerabilities in one component can cascade through the system, creating complex attack scenarios that traditional security approaches may struggle to address.</p>
<p>Consider these real-world scenarios that illustrate the cascading nature of AI agent vulnerabilities:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>The Perception-Brain-Action Attack Chain</strong>:<!-- -->
<ul>
<li>An attacker injects adversarial content into an image processed by the Perception module.</li>
<li>This causes the Brain to misinterpret the context and make an incorrect decision.</li>
<li>The Action module then executes this flawed decision, potentially affecting critical systems.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Perception-Brain-Action Attack Chain" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/perception-brain-action-attack-chain-35dddabc4d34e2c5bf37f60ea71e09b9.png" width="1488" height="837" class="img_ev3q">
2. <strong>The Memory Poisoning Persistence</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li>An attacker uses prompt injection to insert malicious content into the agent's memory.</li>
<li>This poisoned memory persists across sessions and influences future decisions.</li>
<li>Even after the initial attack vector is addressed, the agent continues to make compromised decisions.</li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Memory Poisoning Persistence Attack" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/memory-poisoning-persistence-attack-728b2981937e7823848dc07d602a9e9c.png" width="1488" height="837" class="img_ev3q">
3. <strong>The Tool Escalation Scenario</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li>An attacker manipulates the agent into using an authorised tool in an unintended way.</li>
<li>This creates access to additional capabilities beyond the original security boundaries.</li>
<li>These new capabilities are then used to execute actions that bypass existing security controls.</li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Tool Chain Escalation Scenario" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/tool-chain-escalation-scenario-4ad683f926eed98d01314002b4f89529.png" width="1488" height="837" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>The evolving threat landscape presents additional challenges as AI agents gain new capabilities:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Dynamic Tool Creation</strong>: As agents develop the ability to create their own tools, security teams must address the challenge of evaluating tools that didn't exist during initial security assessments.</li>
<li><strong>Multi-agent Interactions</strong>: When multiple agents work together, security vulnerabilities can propagate across the system, potentially creating new attack vectors that wouldn't exist with isolated agents.</li>
<li><strong>Emergent Behaviours</strong>: Advanced agents may develop emergent behaviours not anticipated by their designers, creating security implications that are difficult to predict and mitigate in advance.</li>
</ul>
<p>These practical implications highlight the need for security approaches specifically designed for the unique challenges presented by AI agents, moving beyond traditional application security paradigms.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="security-principles-for-ai-agents">Security Principles for AI Agents<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/03/04/agentic-ai-part-4#security-principles-for-ai-agents" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Security Principles for AI Agents" title="Direct link to Security Principles for AI Agents">​</a></h2>
<p>While AI agents present novel security challenges, many traditional security principles can be adapted and applied to this new context. Here's how to apply security fundamentals to the unique architecture of AI agents:</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="defense-in-depth-for-ai-systems">Defense-in-Depth for AI Systems<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/03/04/agentic-ai-part-4#defense-in-depth-for-ai-systems" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Defense-in-Depth for AI Systems" title="Direct link to Defense-in-Depth for AI Systems">​</a></h3>
<ol>
<li>
<p><strong>Component-Specific Mitigations</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Brain (LLM) Protections</strong>:<!-- -->
<ul>
<li>Implement robust prompt validation and sanitization.</li>
<li>Develop hierarchical instruction processing with clear priority frameworks.</li>
<li>Create memory integrity verification mechanisms.</li>
<li>Regularly audit and clear sensitive information from agent memory.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Perception Module Safeguards</strong>:<!-- -->
<ul>
<li>Deploy multi-modal input validation across all supported formats.</li>
<li>Implement anomaly detection for unusual input patterns.</li>
<li>Create redundant perception pathways for critical inputs.</li>
<li>Regular testing with adversarial examples to improve robustness.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Action Module Controls</strong>:<!-- -->
<ul>
<li>Implement principle of least privilege for tool access.</li>
<li>Create tool and API usage policies specific to agent capabilities.</li>
<li>Deploy runtime monitoring for unusual or potentially harmful actions.</li>
<li>Develop rollback mechanisms for all agent-initiated changes.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>System-Wide Security Measures</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Containment Strategies</strong>: Sandbox environments where agents can be tested before deployment.</li>
<li><strong>Monitoring Frameworks</strong>: Specialised logging and monitoring designed for AI agent activities.</li>
<li><strong>Incident Response Plans</strong>: Procedures specifically designed for AI agent compromise scenarios.</li>
<li><strong>Regular Security Assessments</strong>: Continuous testing with specialised focus on AI-specific vulnerabilities.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Defense-in-Depth for AI Systems" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/defense-in-depth-ai-systems-36ccb32b036c13aaad5c73539b433c17.png" width="1488" height="837" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="applying-zero-trust-principles-to-ai-agents">Applying Zero Trust Principles to AI Agents<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/03/04/agentic-ai-part-4#applying-zero-trust-principles-to-ai-agents" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Applying Zero Trust Principles to AI Agents" title="Direct link to Applying Zero Trust Principles to AI Agents">​</a></h3>
<p>Taking a page out of what's recommended in the NIST AI Risk Management Framework, applying zero trust architecture to AI systems provides a strong foundation for agent security:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Never Trust, Always Verify</strong>: Treat the agent's components as potentially compromised and verify all transfers between components.</li>
<li><strong>Least Privilege Access</strong>: Limit each agent's access to only the tools and data necessary for its specific function.</li>
<li><strong>Continuous Authentication</strong>: Regularly validate that the agent is operating as expected through behavioral analysis.</li>
<li><strong>Micro-segmentation</strong>: Create boundaries between different agent functions and the systems they interact with.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="developing-ai-specific-security-controls">Developing AI-Specific Security Controls<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/03/04/agentic-ai-part-4#developing-ai-specific-security-controls" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Developing AI-Specific Security Controls" title="Direct link to Developing AI-Specific Security Controls">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Prompt Engineering Security</strong>: Creating prompts with security in mind, including built-in guardrails and instruction validation.</li>
<li><strong>Alignment Techniques</strong>: Using techniques like RLHF (Reinforcement Learning from Human Feedback) to improve agent security posture.</li>
<li><strong>Agent Supervision Models</strong>: Creating overseer agents specifically designed to monitor and validate the actions of operational agents.</li>
<li><strong>Security-Focused Fine-tuning</strong>: Additional training specifically designed to reduce vulnerability to known attack vectors.</li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="OWASP AI Threats and Controls" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/owasp-ai-threats-controls-b89dcce1b70b5a607626d99924264fcb.png" width="1061" height="551" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>The application of these security principles requires a collaborative approach between AI development teams and security professionals, with security considerations integrated throughout the agent development lifecycle rather than applied as an afterthought.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="conclusion-securing-the-future-of-ai-agents">Conclusion: Securing the Future of AI Agents<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/03/04/agentic-ai-part-4#conclusion-securing-the-future-of-ai-agents" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion: Securing the Future of AI Agents" title="Direct link to Conclusion: Securing the Future of AI Agents">​</a></h2>
<p>As we conclude our exploration of agentic AI security, it's clear that these systems require both adaptation of traditional security principles and development of entirely new approaches. The interconnected nature of AI agent components creates complex security challenges that will continue to evolve as agent capabilities advance.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="key-takeaways-from-this-series">Key Takeaways from This Series:<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/03/04/agentic-ai-part-4#key-takeaways-from-this-series" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Key Takeaways from This Series:" title="Direct link to Key Takeaways from This Series:">​</a></h3>
<ol>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/12/agentic-ai-part-1">Part 1</a></strong>: AI agents represent autonomous systems with unique security implications</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/18/agentic-ai-part-2">Part 2</a></strong>: Three evolutionary shifts have fundamentally altered the AI security landscape</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/25/agentic-ai-part-3">Part 3</a></strong>: Each agent component introduces specific vulnerabilities that can cascade through systems</li>
<li><strong>Part 4</strong> (this post): Practical defense strategies require both traditional principles and AI-specific controls</li>
</ol>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="moving-forward">Moving Forward<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/03/04/agentic-ai-part-4#moving-forward" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Moving Forward" title="Direct link to Moving Forward">​</a></h3>
<p>For security professionals facing the immediate challenge of securing AI agents in their environments, the most important first step is developing a comprehensive understanding of how these systems function and the specific vulnerabilities they introduce. This understanding forms the foundation for effective security strategies.</p>
<p>The security landscape will continue evolving as AI agents become more sophisticated. Staying informed about emerging threats, maintaining strong fundamentals, and adapting security practices will be essential for protecting against both current and future risks.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="continue-the-discussion">Continue the Discussion<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/03/04/agentic-ai-part-4#continue-the-discussion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Continue the Discussion" title="Direct link to Continue the Discussion">​</a></h2>
<p>This concludes our four-part exploration of agentic AI security. If you're implementing AI agents in your organization or have insights about securing these systems, I'd love to hear about your experiences and challenges.</p>
<p><strong>Series Navigation</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/12/agentic-ai-part-1">Part 1: The Rise of Agentic AI - A Security Perspective</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/18/agentic-ai-part-2">Part 2: Evolution - Three Critical Shifts in the AI Security Landscape</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/25/agentic-ai-part-3">Part 3: The Anatomy of AI Agents - Security Vulnerabilities</a></li>
<li>Part 4: Practical Security Implications (this post)</li>
</ul>
<p><em>Questions about AI agent security? Reach out via <a href="https://linkedin.com/in/ron-amosa" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">LinkedIn</a> or <a href="mailto:hello@theuncommon.ai" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">email</a>.</em></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="further-readingreferences">Further Reading/References<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/03/04/agentic-ai-part-4#further-readingreferences" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Further Reading/References" title="Direct link to Further Reading/References">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://owasp.org/www-project-top-10-for-large-language-model-applications/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">OWASP Top 10 for Large Language Model Applications</a> - Critical reference for standardized security vulnerabilities in LLM applications</li>
<li><a href="https://www.nist.gov/itl/ai-risk-management-framework" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">NIST AI Risk Management Framework</a> - Comprehensive framework for AI risk assessment and management</li>
<li><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04415" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Targeting the Core: A Simple and Effective Method to Attack RAG-based Agents via Direct LLM Manipulation</a> - Research on vulnerabilities in retrieval-augmented generation systems</li>
<li><a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.07283" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">LLM-to-LLM Prompt Infection Research</a> - Exploration of how malicious prompts can propagate between language models</li>
<li><a href="https://www.anthropic.com/research" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Anthropic's AI Safety Research</a> - Industry research on alignment and safety in advanced AI systems</li>
<li><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1412.6572" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Goodfellow et al. - Explaining and Harnessing Adversarial Examples</a> - Seminal research on adversarial attacks in machine learning systems</li>
<li><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1708.09537" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Dolphin Attack: Inaudible Voice Commands</a> - Research demonstrating audio-based attacks on voice recognition systems</li>
<li><a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2023/07/13/introducing-microsofts-framework-for-building-safer-ai-systems/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Microsoft's AI Security Assessment Framework</a> - Framework for evaluating and enhancing AI system security</li>
</ul>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>agentic-ai</category>
            <category>security</category>
            <category>ai-defense</category>
            <category>security-principles</category>
            <category>cybersecurity-strategy</category>
            <category>ai-security-framework</category>
            <category>enterprise-ai-security</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Part 3: AI Agent Security Vulnerabilities - Brain and Perception Module Analysis]]></title>
            <link>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/25/agentic-ai-part-3</link>
            <guid>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/25/agentic-ai-part-3</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Take a technical deep dive into AI agent anatomy, examining specific security vulnerabilities in the Brain and Perception modules and their implications for enterprise security.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="AI Agent Architecture and Security Vulnerabilities Analysis" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/agentic-ai-part3-cover-69ad73ffc694c9b8e63e0b36e851e4d8.jpg" width="1024" height="576" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>In <a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/12/agentic-ai-part-1">Part 1</a> of this series, we explored how AI agents are transforming enterprise technology with their ability to perceive, decide, and act autonomously.</p>
<p>In <a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/18/agentic-ai-part-2">Part 2</a>, we examined three critical shifts in AI system evolution that have fundamentally altered the security landscape: the transition from rules-based to learning-based systems, the progression from single-task to multi-task capabilities, and the advancement from tool-using to tool-creating agents.</p>
<p>Today, we'll take a technical deep dive into the anatomy of modern AI agents, examining what's happening under the hood and the specific security vulnerabilities in each core component. As organizations rapidly adopt these powerful systems, understanding these vulnerabilities becomes essential for security professionals tasked with protecting their environments.</p>
<p>At its core, an AI agent consists of three primary components: the Brain (typically an LLM) that handles reasoning and decision-making, the Perception module that processes environmental inputs, and the Action module that interacts with systems and tools. Each component introduces unique security challenges that, when combined, create a complex attack surface unlike anything we've seen in traditional systems.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-anatomy-of-an-ai-agent">The Anatomy of an AI Agent<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/25/agentic-ai-part-3#the-anatomy-of-an-ai-agent" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Anatomy of an AI Agent" title="Direct link to The Anatomy of an AI Agent">​</a></h2>
<p>Before diving into specific vulnerabilities, let's get a clear understanding of how modern AI agents operate. Unlike traditional software systems with well-defined input/output relationships, AI agents function much more dynamically and have complex internal processes.</p>
<p>The Brain (LLM) serves as the central nervous system, processing information and making decisions based on its training and current context. The Perception module acts as the agent's senses, interpreting raw data from various sources and converting it to meaningful information the Brain can process. The Action module then functions as the agent's hands, executing commands and interacting with external systems based on the Brain's decisions.</p>
<p>This architecture creates powerful capabilities but also introduces significant security challenges at each layer. What makes these systems particularly concerning from a security perspective is that a vulnerability in one component can cascade through the entire system, potentially affecting multiple downstream systems and data sources connected to the agent.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="AI Agent Components" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/ai-agent-components-60f0b6b93aed454b4450931636dd0007.png" width="1446" height="870" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Let's look at each component's specific security implications in detail.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="component-1-the-brain-llm-core">Component 1: The Brain (LLM Core)<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/25/agentic-ai-part-3#component-1-the-brain-llm-core" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Component 1: The Brain (LLM Core)" title="Direct link to Component 1: The Brain (LLM Core)">​</a></h2>
<p>The Brain component, as the central nervous system in our agent anatomy, deserves special attention from a security perspective precisely because of its sophistication and complexity. The vulnerabilities here are particularly concerning because they target the very core of what makes these systems powerful i.e. their ability to reason and make decisions.</p>
<p>Looking under the hood, we can categorise these vulnerabilities into two main tracks. Many of these align with critical categories in the OWASP Top 10 for Large Language Model Applications, particularly "LLM Prompt Injection" and "Insecure Output Handling":</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="decision-pipeline-vulnerabilities">Decision Pipeline Vulnerabilities<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/25/agentic-ai-part-3#decision-pipeline-vulnerabilities" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Decision Pipeline Vulnerabilities" title="Direct link to Decision Pipeline Vulnerabilities">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Prompt Injection</strong>: At its core, prompt injection exploits a fundamental weakness in how LLMs process instructions - their lack of sophisticated hierarchical processing. Without clear frameworks for prioritizing instructions, attackers can embed malicious commands that override the agent's original instructions. The "Ignore the document" study demonstrated how a simple prefix could bypass contextual safeguards by exploiting the LLM's tendency to give more weight to immediate instructions than established boundaries.</li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Prompt Injection Attack" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/prompt-injection-daa49ea751711f751457c38f37fe292b.png" width="1013" height="577" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>LLM-to-LLM Prompt Infection</strong>: Building on the hierarchical processing weakness, a compromised agent becomes "patient zero" in an infection chain, spreading malicious prompts to other agents in multi-agent systems. This creates a self-replicating infection that silently propagates throughout the ecosystem. While still largely theoretical, recent research (arxiv.org/pdf/2410.07283) suggests this could become a significant threat vector as multi-agent systems become more common.</li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="LLM to LLM Prompt Infection" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/prompt-infection-llm-3a7538e3f8aad0a8726d65d13ac3f0d9.png" width="1034" height="371" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Hierarchical Instruction Processing Weaknesses</strong>: LLMs often lack nuanced hierarchies for processing instructions, making them vulnerable to adversarial prompts that can override contextual safeguards. This structural weakness means that immediate prompts can take precedence over previously established contextual boundaries, creating a fundamental security vulnerability.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="memory-management-risks">Memory Management Risks<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/25/agentic-ai-part-3#memory-management-risks" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Memory Management Risks" title="Direct link to Memory Management Risks">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Memory Manipulation</strong>:<!-- -->
<ul>
<li>Attackers can artificially inflate importance scores of specific memories, ensuring malicious prompts are retrieved more frequently.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Context Limitations</strong>:<!-- -->
<ul>
<li>Limited memory capacity causes agents to lose track of crucial information during extended interactions, creating security blind spots.</li>
<li>Adversaries can perform memory poisoning or context erasure, causing the AI agent to forget essential contextual information. This could involve techniques that overwrite or corrupt the agent's stored memory or disrupt its ability to access relevant past interactions.</li>
<li>A jailbreak attack can leverage a language model agent's poor contextual understanding to bypass safety protocols and generate harmful content. If an AI agent cannot properly differentiate between legitimate instructions and malicious injections due to contextual limitations, it can be coerced into performing unintended and potentially harmful actions.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Data Security Concerns</strong>:<!-- -->
<ul>
<li>Sensitive information stored in memory can be exposed, leading to unauthorized data extraction and knowledge base poisoning.</li>
<li>API usage risks can expose sensitive data to third-party providers, potentially causing data leaks and compliance violations.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>The real-world implications are substantial, with each vulnerability potentially cascading into system-wide failures or security breaches with serious consequences.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Memory Manipulation Attack" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/ai-memoryvuln-memory-manipulation-cf2b73d16a027ae26de16e0649e82acf.png" width="461" height="461" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Context Limitations Vulnerabilities" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/ai-memoryvuln-context-limitations-747762a6d5e10c846c2541bf03ed5191.png" width="501" height="348" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="component-2-the-perception-module">Component 2: The Perception Module<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/25/agentic-ai-part-3#component-2-the-perception-module" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Component 2: The Perception Module" title="Direct link to Component 2: The Perception Module">​</a></h2>
<p>The Perception module functions as the agent's sensory system, converting raw environmental data into structured information for the Brain to process. This component introduces several unique security challenges that expand the attack surface of AI systems, especially given LLMs evolving capabilities with different modalities like audio, visual and video.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="input-validation-challenges">Input Validation Challenges<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/25/agentic-ai-part-3#input-validation-challenges" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Input Validation Challenges" title="Direct link to Input Validation Challenges">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Multi-modal Vulnerabilities</strong>: As agents gain the ability to process text, images, audio, and other input types, each modality introduces its own attack vectors:<!-- -->
<ul>
<li><em>Image-based Attacks</em>: Adversarial images can be crafted to trick vision models into misidentifying objects or extracting misleading information. Research from Goodfellow et al. demonstrated that "imperceptible perturbations" (a disturbance) to images can cause state-of-the-art vision models to completely mis-classify images (e.g., mistaking a panda for a gibbon) with high confidence. In an AI agent context, this could lead to harmful decisions based on manipulated visual data.</li>
<li><em>Audio Manipulation</em>: Voice inputs can be manipulated to include hidden commands or distorted in ways that cause misinterpretation while remaining imperceptible to human listeners. The "Dolphin Attack" research demonstrated how ultrasonic audio can be used to inject commands into voice assistants that humans cannot hear.</li>
<li><em>Cross-modal Attacks</em>: Information from one modality can be used to influence the interpretation of another, creating complex attack scenarios that are difficult to detect and mitigate.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Data Preprocessing Risks</strong>: Before raw data reaches the LLM Brain, it undergoes <em>preprocessing</em> that can be exploited:<!-- -->
<ul>
<li><em>Feature Extraction Manipulation</em>: Attackers can target the feature extraction process, causing the agent to focus on misleading elements of the input.</li>
<li><em>Normalization Attacks</em>: By understanding how inputs are normalised, attackers can craft inputs that appear normal to humans but are interpreted abnormally by the agent.</li>
<li><em>Serialization Vulnerabilities</em>: The conversion of complex multi-modal inputs into formats the LLM can process creates additional attack surfaces where malicious content can be inserted.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Adversarial Attacks</strong>: Specially crafted inputs designed to fool perception systems:<!-- -->
<ul>
<li><em>Evasion Attacks</em>: Inputs designed to avoid detection of harmful content by slightly modifying patterns that would typically trigger safety mechanisms.</li>
<li><em>Data Poisoning</em>: Gradually introducing biased or misleading training examples that can cause systematic misinterpretation of certain input types.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Input Validation Attacks" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/perception-module-input-validation-93f1a225fc772b0f6f36f620b4eb4f27.png" width="1488" height="837" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="environment-interaction-risks">Environment Interaction Risks<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/25/agentic-ai-part-3#environment-interaction-risks" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Environment Interaction Risks" title="Direct link to Environment Interaction Risks">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Sensor Manipulation and Spoofing</strong>: In cases where AI agents interact with physical sensors or data feeds:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Sensor Spoofing</em>: Falsifying sensor data to create a distorted perception of the environment.</li>
<li><em>Feed Tampering</em>: Manipulating data feeds to provide misleading information about the state of systems or environments.</li>
<li><em>Replay Attacks</em>: Recording and replaying previously valid sensor data to mask current conditions.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Reality-Perception Gaps</strong>: Misalignments between the real world and the agent's perception:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Concept Drift</em>: When the agent's understanding of the world becomes outdated compared to reality.</li>
<li><em>Distribution Shift</em>: When the statistical properties of inputs change over time, causing the agent to misinterpret them.</li>
<li><em>Hallucinations</em>: When perception systems "fill in" missing information incorrectly, leading to decisions based on non-existent data.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Trust Boundaries in Perception Systems</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Source Validation Weaknesses</em>: Insufficient verification of input sources, allowing attackers to impersonate legitimate sources.</li>
<li><em>Integrity Verification Gaps</em>: Lack of mechanisms to ensure inputs haven't been tampered with during transmission.</li>
<li><em>Third-party Perception Dependencies</em>: Reliance on external perception models with potentially unknown vulnerabilities.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Environment Interaction Attacks" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/perception-module-environment-interactions-8417ad98175fa381590c327c7b0a79de.png" width="1488" height="837" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>The security implications of perception vulnerabilities are particularly concerning because they occur at the entry point of the agent's decision-making process. A compromised perception module can feed manipulated information to an otherwise secure Brain, resulting in the classic "garbage in, garbage out" problem, but with potentially severe consequences in high-trust or critical systems.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="component-3-the-action-module">Component 3: The Action Module<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/25/agentic-ai-part-3#component-3-the-action-module" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Component 3: The Action Module" title="Direct link to Component 3: The Action Module">​</a></h2>
<p>The Action module is where the AI agent's decisions translate into real-world impact through tool use and system interactions. This component represents the "hands" of the agent and introduces critical security considerations, particularly as agents gain access to more powerful tools and APIs.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="tool-access-control-issues">Tool Access Control Issues<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/25/agentic-ai-part-3#tool-access-control-issues" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Tool Access Control Issues" title="Direct link to Tool Access Control Issues">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Privilege Escalation Vectors</strong>:<!-- -->
<ul>
<li><em>Tool Chaining Vulnerabilities</em>: Agents may combine multiple low-privilege tools in ways that effectively create higher-privilege capabilities, similar to how traditional privilege escalation attacks work.</li>
<li><em>Unintended Tool Functionality</em>: Tools designed for one purpose may have secondary functions that can be exploited when used in unintended ways.</li>
<li><em>Emergent Permissions</em>: As agents become more sophisticated, they may discover creative ways to use authorized tools to achieve unauthorized outcomes, particularly when multiple tools are available.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>API Security Considerations</strong>:<!-- -->
<ul>
<li><em>Key Management Risks</em>: How API keys and credentials are stored, accessed, and used by the agent creates potential exposure points.</li>
<li><em>Rate Limiting Bypasses</em>: Agents might unintentionally (or if compromised, intentionally) attempt to bypass API rate limits, creating denial-of-service vulnerabilities.</li>
<li><em>Data Transmission Security</em>: Ensuring secure transmission of data between the agent and external APIs requires robust encryption and validation.</li>
<li><em>API Scope Expansion</em>: Over time, APIs tend to gain functionality, potentially giving agents access to capabilities beyond what was initially evaluated for security.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Monitoring Execution of Agent Actions</strong>:<!-- -->
<ul>
<li><em>Visibility Challenges</em>: Traditional security monitoring may struggle to interpret the context and intent behind agent-initiated actions.</li>
<li><em>Attribution Difficulties</em>: Determining whether an action was the result of a legitimate agent decision or a security compromise can be complex.</li>
<li><em>Audit Trail Requirements</em>: Special considerations for logging agent decisions and actions in ways that allow for meaningful security review.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Tool Access Control Challenges" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/tool-access-control-34ec17e6f50a12f963ed18dbfb55b026.png" width="1024" height="768" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="output-processing-vulnerabilities">Output Processing Vulnerabilities<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/25/agentic-ai-part-3#output-processing-vulnerabilities" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Output Processing Vulnerabilities" title="Direct link to Output Processing Vulnerabilities">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Unvalidated Output Execution</strong>:<!-- -->
<ul>
<li><em>Injection Vulnerabilities</em>: Without proper validation, outputs from the Brain could contain malicious instructions that get executed in target systems.</li>
<li><em>Command Interpretation Risks</em>: Ambiguous outputs may be interpreted differently by receiving systems than intended by the agent.</li>
<li><em>Missing Output Sanitization</em>: Direct execution of agent outputs without proper filtering can lead to inappropriate or harmful actions.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Output Context Misalignment</strong>:<!-- -->
<ul>
<li><em>Environmental Mismatch</em>: Actions appropriate in one context may be harmful in another when the agent misunderstands its operational environment.</li>
<li><em>Temporal Inconsistency</em>: Actions may become inappropriate due to timing issues between decision-making and execution.</li>
<li><em>Target System Confusion</em>: The agent may direct outputs to incorrect systems if authentication and routing mechanisms are inadequate.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Feedback Loop Vulnerabilities</strong>:<!-- -->
<ul>
<li><em>False Success Signals</em>: When output execution status is misreported, agents may continue harmful action patterns.</li>
<li><em>Error Handling Weaknesses</em>: Improper handling of failed actions can lead to repeated attempts with increasing levels of privilege or access.</li>
<li><em>Adaptation to Restrictions</em>: Agents may learn to work around output restrictions over time, finding alternative ways to execute blocked actions.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Output Processing Vulnerabilities" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/output-processing-vulnerabilities-77c4471c42ce950e61affb4c47574b09.png" width="1024" height="768" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>The Action module presents unique security challenges because it represents the point where AI decisions directly impact systems and data. A compromised Action module might execute harmful commands while appearing to operate normally, making detection particularly challenging. As agents gain capabilities to create and use tools dynamically, the security considerations around the Action module become increasingly complex.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="key-takeaways">Key Takeaways<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/25/agentic-ai-part-3#key-takeaways" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Key Takeaways" title="Direct link to Key Takeaways">​</a></h2>
<p>Understanding AI agent vulnerabilities requires a component-by-component analysis:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Brain Module (LLM)</strong>: Vulnerable to prompt injection, memory manipulation, and hierarchical instruction processing weaknesses</li>
<li><strong>Perception Module</strong>: Susceptible to multi-modal attacks, preprocessing manipulation, and sensor spoofing</li>
<li><strong>Action Module</strong>: Exposed to privilege escalation, unvalidated output execution, and feedback loop vulnerabilities</li>
</ol>
<p>These vulnerabilities become particularly dangerous when they cascade across components, creating attack chains that can compromise entire systems.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="continue-the-series">Continue the Series<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/25/agentic-ai-part-3#continue-the-series" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Continue the Series" title="Direct link to Continue the Series">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Next up</strong>: <a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/03/04/agentic-ai-part-4">Part 4: Practical Security Implications</a>, where we'll examine how these vulnerabilities create practical security challenges and discuss approaches for mitigating these risks.</p>
<p><strong>Previous</strong>: <a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/18/agentic-ai-part-2">Part 2: Evolution - Three Critical Shifts in the AI Security Landscape</a></p>
<p><em>Questions about AI agent vulnerabilities? Reach out via <a href="https://linkedin.com/in/ron-amosa" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">LinkedIn</a> or <a href="mailto:hello@theuncommon.ai" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">email</a>.</em></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>agentic-ai</category>
            <category>security</category>
            <category>ai-vulnerabilities</category>
            <category>llm-security</category>
            <category>ai-architecture</category>
            <category>prompt-injection-attacks</category>
            <category>enterprise-ai-security</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Part 2: Evolution - Three Critical Shifts in the AI Security Landscape]]></title>
            <link>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/18/agentic-ai-part-2</link>
            <guid>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/18/agentic-ai-part-2</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Examine three fundamental shifts in AI system evolution that have dramatically altered the security landscape: from rules-based to learning-based systems, single-task to multi-task capabilities, and tool-using to tool-creating agents.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Three Critical Shifts in the AI Security Landscape" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/agentic-ai-part2-cover-103e3ab56bd9ed964ca742bc458173ae.jpg" width="1024" height="576" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>In <a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/12/agentic-ai-part-1">Part 1</a> of this series, we explored how AI agents—autonomous systems capable of perceiving, deciding, and acting—are transforming enterprise technology. We examined their core components (Brain, Perception, and Action modules) and why these systems matter now more than ever.</p>
<p>Today, we'll examine three fundamental shifts in how AI systems have evolved—transitions that have dramatically altered the security landscape. These aren't just technical changes; they represent fundamental transformations in how AI systems operate, the risks they pose, and the challenges organizations face in securing them.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-evolution-creates-new-attack-surfaces">The Evolution Creates New Attack Surfaces<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/18/agentic-ai-part-2#the-evolution-creates-new-attack-surfaces" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Evolution Creates New Attack Surfaces" title="Direct link to The Evolution Creates New Attack Surfaces">​</a></h2>
<p>The evolution of artificial intelligence has brought about fundamental changes in how AI systems are architected and deployed. As these systems become more sophisticated, they've gained significant capabilities while also introducing new attack surfaces and vulnerabilities that could put organizations at risk. At the heart of many modern AI systems are pre-trained language models (PLMs), which serve as the foundation for increasingly sophisticated AI agents.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="understanding-plm-vulnerabilities-in-modern-ai-systems">Understanding PLM Vulnerabilities in Modern AI Systems<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/18/agentic-ai-part-2#understanding-plm-vulnerabilities-in-modern-ai-systems" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Understanding PLM Vulnerabilities in Modern AI Systems" title="Direct link to Understanding PLM Vulnerabilities in Modern AI Systems">​</a></h2>
<p>Researchers have found that pre-trained language models (PLMs) are particularly susceptible to adversarial attacks, manipulating the models behaviour to produce intentionally wrong outputs, or evade safety controls. While adversarial attacks on standard LLMs might be contained to a single system or task, LLM-based agents integrate with multiple systems through their action modules - accessing tools, databases, and APIs. This broader system access means a single compromised decision can trigger multiple downstream actions across connected systems.</p>
<p>AI Architecture Vulnerabilities</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="AI Threat Flow Diagram" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/ai-threat-flow-diagram-231c48e1c8fc1438ed9dd26b42f9fe8b.png" width="1142" height="922" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>AI Threat Flow Diagram</p>
<p>These vulnerabilities surface through multiple attack vectors:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Dataset poisoning:</strong> Attackers can manipulate the training data to embed harmful behaviors</li>
<li><strong>Backdoor attacks:</strong> Hidden triggers can be planted to make the model behave maliciously in specific situations</li>
<li><strong>Prompt-specific attacks:</strong> Carefully crafted inputs can override the model's safety controls</li>
<li><strong>Multi-modal vulnerabilities:</strong> Adversarial inputs from images or audio can deceive the perception module</li>
<li><strong>Action module exploitation:</strong> Maliciously modified instructions can trigger harmful real-world actions</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="key-security-impacting-transitions">Key Security-Impacting Transitions<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/18/agentic-ai-part-2#key-security-impacting-transitions" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Key Security-Impacting Transitions" title="Direct link to Key Security-Impacting Transitions">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="rules-based-to-learning-based-evolution">Rules-based to Learning-based Evolution<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/18/agentic-ai-part-2#rules-based-to-learning-based-evolution" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Rules-based to Learning-based Evolution" title="Direct link to Rules-based to Learning-based Evolution">​</a></h3>
<p>Early AI systems were built on symbolic AI foundations, employing logical rules and symbolic representations to replicate human reasoning patterns in an explicit and interpretable way. However, this approach gave way to more dynamic, learning-based agents as the field progressed. The transition began with reactive agents that could interact with their environments in real-time, followed by the integration of reinforcement learning (RL) which enabled agents to learn and improve through experience rather than relying solely on pre-programmed rules.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Rules-based AI" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/ai-rules-based-43b928e536f64a4a3fb336fcdd78e319.png" width="1078" height="650" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Fig 1. Rules-based</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Learning-based AI" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/ai-learning-based-d4b4cfbaf7e5fef3445b2988cf6ef506.png" width="974" height="650" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Fig 2. Learning-based</p>
<p><strong>Security Implications:</strong></p>
<p>Critical Vulnerabilities:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Prompt injection susceptibility:</strong> LLMs can be subverted by malicious prompts that override their intended purpose</li>
<li><strong>Infection propagation:</strong> In multi-agent systems, a compromised learning-based agent can spread the "infection" to other agents</li>
<li><strong>Memory manipulation:</strong> Attackers can manipulate memory retrieval by inflating the importance score of malicious prompts</li>
<li><strong>Instruction hierarchy fragility:</strong> Learning-based models often lack structured hierarchies for processing instructions, so an attacker could bypass security measures by injecting instructions that the model might prioritise over its own safety instructions.</li>
</ul>
<p>Systemic Challenges:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Transparency gaps:</strong> Learning-based systems create "black box" decision-making</li>
<li><strong>Data vulnerability:</strong> AI queries and responses can be manipulated for theft or corruption</li>
<li><strong>Bias perpetuation:</strong> Learning-based systems may amplify biases present in training data</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="single-task-to-multi-task-progression">Single-task to Multi-task Progression<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/18/agentic-ai-part-2#single-task-to-multi-task-progression" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Single-task to Multi-task Progression" title="Direct link to Single-task to Multi-task Progression">​</a></h3>
<p>Initially, agents were designed for specific, narrow tasks. The field has evolved toward multi-task agents capable of handling diverse responsibilities, including multi-modal processing of text, images, and audio. Multi-agent systems (MAS) have emerged to tackle complex problems through collaboration between specialised agents.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Single-Task AI" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/ai-single-task-ef4415e2187fc4377c0bb37a006f62a1.png" width="918" height="552" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Fig 3. Single-Task</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Multi-Task AI" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/ai-multi-task-2d751995a21c3199cfbc4732ee7ebd07.png" width="1150" height="552" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Fig 4. Multi-Task</p>
<p><strong>Security Implications:</strong></p>
<p>Architectural Vulnerabilities:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Expanded attack surface:</strong> Direct database access creates multiple entry points</li>
<li><strong>Complex infection pathways:</strong> Coordinated attacks can exploit multiple agents simultaneously</li>
<li><strong>Insufficient defences:</strong> Current agent-level protections struggle with core LLM vulnerabilities</li>
</ul>
<p>Operational Challenges:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Context maintenance:</strong> Difficulty maintaining awareness across extended interactions</li>
<li><strong>Social simulation risks:</strong> Unsecured memory retrieval systems expose simulations to prompt infection</li>
<li><strong>Coordination exploitation:</strong> Attackers can leverage agent-to-agent communication channels</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="tool-using-to-tool-creating-advancement">Tool-using to Tool-creating Advancement<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/18/agentic-ai-part-2#tool-using-to-tool-creating-advancement" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Tool-using to Tool-creating Advancement" title="Direct link to Tool-using to Tool-creating Advancement">​</a></h3>
<p>Early agents had limited interaction with their environment. Modern agents not only use existing tools but can create new ones by abstracting task requirements or integrating existing capabilities. This includes generating executable programs and even debugging themselves.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Tool Use AI" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/ai-tool-use-1d45cc64dd2e614ed7093c1d7bd9c2d4.png" width="888" height="586" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Tool Use</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Tool Creating AI" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/ai-tool-creating-5e93224aae2954c1b1d681a7c10950fe.png" width="1174" height="826" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Tool Creating</p>
<p><strong>Security Implications:</strong></p>
<p>Primary Concerns:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Novel attack vectors:</strong> Generative AI can identify vulnerabilities and create new attack scenarios</li>
<li><strong>Dual-use capabilities:</strong> AI agents can be weaponised for both offensive and defensive purposes</li>
<li><strong>Gateway risks:</strong> Compromised AI agents can enable unauthorised access to sensitive systems</li>
</ul>
<p>Emerging Challenges:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Detection complexity:</strong> Traditional security monitoring may miss AI-generated threats</li>
<li><strong>Rapid evolution:</strong> Security measures must adapt to keep pace with AI tool creation</li>
<li><strong>Ethical boundaries:</strong> Tool-creating capabilities raise questions about autonomous system limits</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="practical-implications">Practical Implications<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/18/agentic-ai-part-2#practical-implications" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Practical Implications" title="Direct link to Practical Implications">​</a></h2>
<p>With such dramatic shifts in system complexity and architecture, you would be forgiven for assuming we need to completely reinvent our security practices. However, the opposite is true. Organisations adopting advanced AI systems should recognise that fundamental security principles remain more relevant than ever.</p>
<p>The core practices that security professionals have long advocated – principle of least privilege, defence in depth, threat modelling, and robust authentication and authorisation – provide the essential foundation for securing AI systems.</p>
<p>Take the principle of least privilege, for example. Just as we've always limited user access to only what's necessary for their role, this same principle becomes even more crucial when applied to AI agents that can interact with multiple systems and make autonomous decisions.</p>
<p>The principle hasn't changed – we're just applying it to a more sophisticated actor.</p>
<p>What changes is not these fundamental principles, but rather how we apply them to AI's unique characteristics:</p>
<ul>
<li>For learning-based systems: Traditional input validation expands to include monitoring training data integrity and model behaviour</li>
<li>For multi-task systems: Principle of least privilege becomes even more critical when managing permissions across multiple AI capabilities</li>
<li>For tool-creating systems: Standard runtime monitoring practices adapt to track AI-generated code and tools</li>
</ul>
<p>The 'beast' may look different, but the principles of securing interconnected systems remain the same. Organisations that maintain strong security fundamentals while understanding AI's specific characteristics will be better positioned to manage these emerging technologies safely.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="key-takeaways">Key Takeaways<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/18/agentic-ai-part-2#key-takeaways" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Key Takeaways" title="Direct link to Key Takeaways">​</a></h2>
<p>Understanding these three evolutionary shifts is crucial for security professionals:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Learning-based systems</strong> introduce unpredictability and new attack vectors like prompt injection</li>
<li><strong>Multi-task capabilities</strong> expand attack surfaces and create complex interaction patterns</li>
<li><strong>Tool-creating abilities</strong> enable novel threats that traditional security models weren't designed to handle</li>
</ol>
<p>The fundamental security principles remain valid, but their application must evolve to address AI's unique characteristics.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="continue-the-series">Continue the Series<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/18/agentic-ai-part-2#continue-the-series" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Continue the Series" title="Direct link to Continue the Series">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Next up</strong>: <a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/25/agentic-ai-part-3">Part 3: The Anatomy of AI Agents - Security Vulnerabilities</a>, where we'll take a technical deep dive into the anatomy of modern AI agents, examining specific vulnerabilities in each core component.</p>
<p><strong>Previous</strong>: <a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/12/agentic-ai-part-1">Part 1: The Rise of Agentic AI - A Security Perspective</a></p>
<p><em>Questions about AI evolution and security? Reach out via <a href="https://linkedin.com/in/ron-amosa" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">LinkedIn</a> or <a href="mailto:hello@theuncommon.ai" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">email</a>.</em></p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="further-reading">Further Reading<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/18/agentic-ai-part-2#further-reading" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Further Reading" title="Direct link to Further Reading">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li>Zhang, C., et al. "The Rise and Potential of Large Language Model Based Agents: A Survey" (2023)</li>
<li>Zhu, K., et al. "PromptBench: Towards Evaluating the Robustness of Large Language Models on Adversarial Prompts" (2023)</li>
<li>Chen, X., et al. "How Robust is GPT-3.5 to Predecessors? A Comprehensive Study on Language Understanding Tasks" (2023)</li>
<li>Qiao, Z., et al. "CREATOR: Tool Creation for Disentangling Abstract and Concrete Reasoning of Large Language Models" (2023)</li>
<li>Gu, T., et al. "Identifying Vulnerabilities in the Machine Learning Model Supply Chain" (2017)</li>
<li>Chen, X., et al. "BadNL: Backdoor Attacks Against NLP Models" in ACSAC '21: Annual Computer Security Applications Conference (2021)</li>
<li>Li, Z., et al. "BFClass: A Backdoor-Free Text Classification Framework" in Findings of ACL: EMNLP 2021</li>
<li>Shi, Y., et al. "PromptAttack: Prompt-based Attack for Language Models via Gradient Search" in NLPCC 2022</li>
<li>Perez, F. and Ribeiro, I. "Ignore Previous Prompt: Attack Techniques for Language Models" (2022)</li>
<li>Liang, P., et al. "Holistic Evaluation of Language Models" (2022)</li>
<li>Gururangan, S., et al. "Whose Language Counts as High Quality? Measuring Language Ideologies in Text Data Selection" in EMNLP 2022</li>
<li>Liu, Y., et al. "Prompt Injection Attack Against LLM-Integrated Applications" (2023)</li>
</ul>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>agentic-ai</category>
            <category>security</category>
            <category>ai-evolution</category>
            <category>machine-learning</category>
            <category>threat-landscape</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Part 1: The Rise of Agentic AI - A Security Perspective]]></title>
            <link>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/12/agentic-ai-part-1</link>
            <guid>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/12/agentic-ai-part-1</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Explore how AI agents are transforming enterprise technology and the security implications of autonomous systems capable of perceiving, deciding, and acting.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="The Rise of Agentic AI" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/agentic-ai-part1-cover-3b4c5aaa6c0f7167c5f10bb39d8e57ce.jpg" width="1279" height="720" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Artificial Intelligence agents are transforming how enterprises operate, but they're also introducing unprecedented security challenges. These autonomous systems can perceive their environment, make decisions, and take actions—capabilities that make them incredibly powerful and potentially dangerous.</p>
<p>As organizations rush to adopt agentic AI systems, with industry predictions of 25% of companies launching pilots by 2025, understanding the security implications becomes critical. This four-part series examines agentic AI from a security professional's perspective, exploring both the opportunities and the risks these systems present.</p>
<p>The rise of autonomous AI agents represents more than just technological advancement—it's a fundamental shift in how we think about AI systems. Unlike traditional software that follows predetermined paths, AI agents can adapt, learn, and make independent decisions. When these capabilities are compromised, the consequences extend far beyond typical software vulnerabilities.</p>
<p>To understand how these systems create new security paradigms, we need to start with the fundamental building block: the AI Agent.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="understanding-ai-agents">Understanding AI Agents<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/12/agentic-ai-part-1#understanding-ai-agents" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Understanding AI Agents" title="Direct link to Understanding AI Agents">​</a></h2>
<p>An AI agent is defined as an entity capable of <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2309.07864v3" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">"perceiving its surroundings using sensors, making decisions, and then taking actions in response using actuators"</a>. This definition appears consistently across recent research papers with little debate about its core meaning.</p>
<p>I was surprised to discover from <a href="https://www.cs.cmu.edu/~motionplanning/papers/sbp_papers/integrated1/woodridge_intelligent_agents.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wooldridge &amp; Jennings' seminal 1995 paper</a> that this conception of an agent - as an entity that can perceive, reason, and act - is considered a "weak notion" of agency. Stronger notions exist that explicitly model agents in terms of mentalistic concepts like beliefs, desires, and intentions.</p>
<p>What makes "agents" a special concept?</p>
<p>Isn't it just a computer programme at the end of the day?</p>
<p>Yes, it is a computer programme - but the key distinguishing feature is "autonomy". The AI agent is an entity that (to varying degrees) <em>thinks</em> for itself, makes decisions on its own, and if it has the "tools" available to it, will continue acting on its own decisions until it achieves the goal we've given it.</p>
<p>Recent research agrees with this view. <a href="https://arxiv.org/html/2401.03428v1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">"Exploring Large Language Model based Intelligent Agents"</a> emphasises that the key aspect of agents is their autonomy to carry out tasks in diverse environments, using past experiences and knowledge . They can even modify their plans during execution.</p>
<p>This capability represents both tremendous potential and significant risk.</p>
<p>So, how does the agent do this? An AI agent has three primary components:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Brain Module:</strong> This encompasses natural language interaction, knowledge, memory, reasoning, planning, and transferability.</li>
<li><strong>Perception Module:</strong> This handles textual, visual, auditory, and other input types.</li>
<li><strong>Action Module:</strong> This includes textual output, tool use, and embodied action.</li>
</ol>
<p>This diagram from <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.07864" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">"The Rise and Potential of Large Language Model Based Agents: A Survey"</a> illustrates these core components and their sub-functions, showing how agents can think and act autonomously:</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Diagram of agent components showing perception, inputs; action, text, tools; and brain, memory knowledge, decision making." src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/ai-agent-components-diagram-54f676a6d0f733c49b83f013a0df36d2.png" width="1446" height="870" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>core components of an AI agent.</p>
<p>For this series, we'll focus on this "weaker" notion of agents. Rather than getting lost in discussions of human-like mental states, we'll examine agents from a software engineering perspective, particularly what this means for security vulnerabilities.</p>
<p>While there are complex aspects of agent architecture involving various types of memory, reasoning, and planning, we'll keep it high level for now. Part 3 of this series will provide a technical deep dive into the agent architecture.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="why-this-matters-for-security-professionals">Why This Matters for Security Professionals<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/12/agentic-ai-part-1#why-this-matters-for-security-professionals" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Why This Matters for Security Professionals" title="Direct link to Why This Matters for Security Professionals">​</a></h2>
<p>Before diving deeper into the series, it's worth understanding why agentic AI represents a paradigm shift for cybersecurity:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Expanded Attack Surface</strong>: Agents interact with multiple systems, APIs, and data sources</li>
<li><strong>Autonomous Decision Making</strong>: Compromised agents can make harmful decisions without human oversight</li>
<li><strong>Dynamic Behavior</strong>: Agent actions aren't always predictable, making traditional security monitoring challenging</li>
<li><strong>Cascading Effects</strong>: A vulnerability in one agent component can impact entire connected systems</li>
</ul>
<p>These characteristics require security professionals to think beyond traditional application security models.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="from-agents-to-agentic-systems">From Agents to Agentic Systems<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/12/agentic-ai-part-1#from-agents-to-agentic-systems" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to From Agents to Agentic Systems" title="Direct link to From Agents to Agentic Systems">​</a></h2>
<p>In researching "Agentic AI," I discovered a confusing landscape of terms often used interchangeably, leading to misunderstandings about what exactly constitutes an Agentic system.</p>
<p>Among various perspectives, Anthropic's blog post <a href="https://www.anthropic.com/research/building-effective-agents" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">"Building effective agents"</a> offers the clearest framework for understanding the relationship between agents and agentic systems.</p>
<p>Their customers often describe "AI agents" in two distinct ways:</p>
<ol>
<li>Fully autonomous software operating independently</li>
<li>Workflows with "predefined code paths"</li>
</ol>
<p>Anthropic classifies both as <em>Agentic Systems</em> but makes a crucial architectural distinction:</p>
<ul>
<li>A "workflow" follows a predefined pathway with set tasks</li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="AI Workflow Diagram" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/ai-workflow-diagram-04aae7e0f259246f7f94a48be5b16d6a.png" width="2232" height="929" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>workflow: prompt-chaining</p>
<ul>
<li>An "agent" operates with true autonomy</li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="AI Agent Autonomous Diagram" src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/ai-agent-autonomous-7eecbb811454796c809c77c1eba5d5f2.png" width="2232" height="929" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>agent: autonomous</p>
<p>While both types of agentic systems have an LLM-based brain component at their core, true agents are distinguished by one key characteristic: autonomy.</p>
<p>This autonomy explains much of the hype around agents and why they often spark discussions about AGI/ASI. At its core, the agent architecture attempts to replicate human intelligence in AI form.</p>
<p>It is an entity designed to:</p>
<ul>
<li>Think and reason independently</li>
<li>Plan and execute actions</li>
<li>Monitor its environment for feedback</li>
<li>Learn continuously</li>
<li>Record experiences and lessons</li>
<li>Operate without constant human oversight</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="why-agents-matter-now">Why Agents Matter Now<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/12/agentic-ai-part-1#why-agents-matter-now" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Why Agents Matter Now" title="Direct link to Why Agents Matter Now">​</a></h2>
<p>The rise of AI agents represents a fundamental shift in how AI systems are being deployed and operated.</p>
<p>The industry recognises this transformation:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www2.deloitte.com/us/en/insights/industry/technology/technology-media-and-telecom-predictions/2025/autonomous-generative-ai-agents-still-under-development.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Deloitte</a> predicts that by 2025, 25% of companies using generative AI will launch agentic AI pilots or proofs of concept, growing to 50% by 2027</li>
<li><a href="https://www.gartner.com/en/newsroom/press-releases/2024-10-21-gartner-identifies-the-top-10-strategic-technology-trends-for-2025" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Gartner</a> places agentic AI at the top of its strategic technology trends for 2025.</li>
</ul>
<p>Major tech companies are already positioning themselves in this space. Microsoft's Copilot leads in enterprise adoption, while companies like OpenAI and HubSpot are heavily investing in agent architectures.</p>
<p>What makes this shift significant is the evolution from human-directed tools to autonomous agents. These agents can:</p>
<ul>
<li>Access and utilise tools independently</li>
<li>Reason through complex situations</li>
<li>Make and execute decisions</li>
<li>Accomplish goals without human intervention</li>
</ul>
<p>While Artificial General Intelligence (AGI) and Artificial Super Intelligence (ASI) remain distant goals, industry leaders like Sam Altman and Dario Amodei view agentic AI as an essential stepping-stone toward AGI. This makes understanding these systems crucial - not just for their immediate impact on technology and business, but for their role in what could be a historic breakthrough.</p>
<p>However, these new capabilities bring new risks. While agents can dramatically improve efficiency and automation, they also introduce novel attack vectors and security considerations that many organisations aren't prepared to address.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="whats-coming-in-this-series">What's Coming in This Series<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/12/agentic-ai-part-1#whats-coming-in-this-series" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What's Coming in This Series" title="Direct link to What's Coming in This Series">​</a></h2>
<p>This is the first in a four-part exploration of agentic AI security:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Understanding AI Agents</strong> (this post) - Foundational concepts and definitions</li>
<li><strong>Evolution and Security Shifts</strong> - How AI system changes have altered the threat landscape</li>
<li><strong>Technical Deep Dive</strong> - Vulnerabilities in agent architecture components</li>
<li><strong>Defense Strategies</strong> - Practical security approaches and recommendations</li>
</ol>
<p>Each post builds on the previous ones, providing both theoretical understanding and practical insights for security professionals working with these emerging technologies.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="continue-the-discussion">Continue the Discussion<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/12/agentic-ai-part-1#continue-the-discussion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Continue the Discussion" title="Direct link to Continue the Discussion">​</a></h2>
<p>This post is part of an ongoing exploration of AI security challenges. If you're working with AI agents in your organization or have insights to share about agentic AI security, I'd love to hear about your experiences.</p>
<p><strong>Next up</strong>: <a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/2025/02/18/agentic-ai-part-2">Part 2: Evolution - Three Critical Shifts in the AI Security Landscape</a>, where we'll examine how fundamental changes in AI systems have created new security paradigms.</p>
<p><em>Have questions or thoughts on agentic AI security? Feel free to reach out via <a href="https://linkedin.com/in/ron-amosa" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">LinkedIn</a> or <a href="mailto:hello@theuncommon.ai" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">email</a>.</em></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>agentic-ai</category>
            <category>security</category>
            <category>ai-agents</category>
            <category>artificial-intelligence</category>
            <category>cybersecurity</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Winter is coming...]]></title>
            <link>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/winter-is-coming</link>
            <guid>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/winter-is-coming</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Brief check-in teasing upcoming newsletter content and sharing 2025 intentions around AI building and community involvement. Essential reading for understanding]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Winter is coming..." src="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/assets/images/winter-is-coming-3005e1387357fadf57cb0f79ef431b99.png" width="2464" height="1856" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Talofa reader,</p>
<p>It’s February already, but happy 2025, and gong xi fa chai 🐍 all the same!</p>
<p>This isn’t an actual post, but more of a “hey, checking in and letting you know I’ve got somerantswriting coming!”</p>
<p>This is already shaping up to be a weird year, what with everything going on in AI, U.S. Politics, our shitty politics and just the overall decline of human society (😂😭).</p>
<p>My outlook and goals this year (as usual) are a bit chaotic, but I’m getting better at just accepting that, having a bias for action, but also be willing to axe something that doesn’t feel “right”. This could be seen as “fickle”, I know, but I think with enough years of life experience, it’s hard to bullshit myself into thinking I like something I know I clearly don’t.</p>
<p>Would you look at that, the “just checking in post” is starting to turn into a “let me speak on a few things while I have your attention”.</p>
<p>Anyway, while I have you (lol), just quickly, this year- leaning into AI hard, building things, posting things, presenting things, community things, business things and also, possibly mype’a, and some aganu’u, and a few AI/ML certifications.</p>
<p>Lots on, dot com.</p>
<p>Talk soon,</p>
<p>Manuia feau ma galuega o le aso!</p>
<p>p.s. I’ve had a few youngin’s hit me up lately for tech career advice, and I tend to get a few of these requests throughout the year. I sent them this post from last year, which is still as true today as it was when I wrote it.</p>
<p>And, not just for pasifika, but imho, anyone, who’s not a complete sycophant for the corporation-</p>
<p>Have a read (it’s free), pass it on to anyone you think needs to read this (remember: Wu-Tang is for the kids)</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>AI-Sovereignty-Governance</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The End of Everything]]></title>
            <link>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/the-end-of-everything</link>
            <guid>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/the-end-of-everything</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Reflects on mortality and seasonal life transitions arguing that endings are essential to meaning and authentic human experience. Essential reading for understa]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Talofa reader,</p>
<p>Looking back on this year, or any year for that matter, but more intensely in recent years, you see the course of the year, the events that happened, the things you went through at work, at home, in the gym and with your social circles, the heaters and rain in winter, the fans and singlets out in Summer.</p>
<p>The ups, the downs, normal life shit.</p>
<p>But as the years stack up, the ups and downs aren't jagged spikes anymore, they've started to flow out as "arcs" of your years, and across those arcs, where jobs started and relationships ended, life events changed the course of your world, these became the seasons of your mortality.</p>
<p>I'm free-styling this piece because I had an observation about my life, sitting here at my desk, working from home on a weekday morning.</p>
<p>I say observation, because it's not a realisation — it's not an epiphany I had at my desk, and now suddenly I see the world differently.</p>
<p>I've known these things for a while, because I like to think a lot, and my realisations about how this life ebbs and flows came and went, in my late teens, my late 20s, and through to turning 40.</p>
<p>I'm at a stage in life where I can see the seasons of life happening, sometimes they span years, other times, months.</p>
<p>Nothing lasts forever, and everything must have an end.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="seasons-of-life">Seasons of Life<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/the-end-of-everything#seasons-of-life" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Seasons of Life" title="Direct link to Seasons of Life">​</a></h2>
<p>Everything has its season, and I'm not sure if it's experience or maturity that brings this about, but the older I get, the more I am aware of the end of a season. Is this the last workshop I run? Is this the last newsletter I'm going to write? Am I over this job and need to move on?</p>
<p>Not, "the last" as in "am I going to die tomorrow?"</p>
<p>The "last" as in — do I still want to do this anymore? Why<em>am</em>I still doing it?</p>
<p>Like the fighter who (arguably "should") knows when to hang up the gloves, because the fire or the fight isn't there anymore, so too do I feel the questions rise internally about anything I have been toiling away on, and gradually begin to feel — past the legitimate and ordinary doubts one gets when doing anything for a short time, past the challenges that come with any venture — to even call it a question is actually incorrect, because the "thing" rising up in you is not a question, it's the voice that says "it's time."</p>
<p>It's not a question of if anymore, it seems that question has been answered; it's a question of when.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="things-have-to-end">Things Have to End<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/the-end-of-everything#things-have-to-end" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Things Have to End" title="Direct link to Things Have to End">​</a></h2>
<p>My friend wrote a newsletter about viewing failure (“The Joy of Failure &amp; Error”). I think reviewing a lot of these concepts and ideas we had as young people without the benefit of life experience, scars, epiphanies etc., and seeing the many new facets to them, like how "failure is not fatal" (unless it's skydiving hahaha) but also, and sometimes morbidly death, is necessary.</p>
<p>Things have to end.</p>
<p>There was an article on a scientist researching how to essentially live forever (nothing new) by saving your brain. Great. I could go into numerous stories of humans (namely billionaires) trying to live forever, and why I think that's an illness or parasite of a non-human mindset… but I digress.</p>
<p>Depth of life, yes.</p>
<p>Length of life, why?</p>
<p>More is not synonymous with "better". Sure, if it took more time to guarantee the depth of life would be achieved, maybe?</p>
<p>But this pursuit of immortality doesn't seem rooted in the human experience to me. A parasitic experience where the focus is on just existing, prolonging the experience, sounds like what the base objective of drug addiction is.</p>
<p>I was big on vampire movies growing up, watching these suave immortals, with eternity to learn everything so they were always super smart, cultured, knowledgeable and wise. All things I aspire to in a way. But one theme that came through in several of these movies was the negative experience of immortality — seeing every loved one you ever had grow old and die, leaving you alone, with all your great characteristics and traits, but ultimately alone.</p>
<p>If humans are social creatures, and having immortality leaves you essentially alone, then a person with immortality is no longer human, because an essential part of the human experience is that it ends.</p>
<p>But that's what makes it beautiful:</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-freedom-of-fewer-fucks">The Freedom of Fewer Fucks<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/the-end-of-everything#the-freedom-of-fewer-fucks" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Freedom of Fewer Fucks" title="Direct link to The Freedom of Fewer Fucks">​</a></h2>
<p>I think having been through more of life, you get less "gives a fuck" about a lot of things.</p>
<p>I think the more life you've been through and understand, the fewer fucks you give about a lot of things.</p>
<p>Not because you've given up on life, and just want to watch the world burn like Heath Ledger's Joker, but because if you truly do "get it", you understand there's actually very few things in life to get worked up about.</p>
<p>I read Mark Manson's "The Subtle Art of Not Giving a Fuck" and of course a lot of that resonates when you're looking for permission to not give a fuck about all the things encroaching on your life, affecting your mental well-being.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="escaping-the-productivity-trap">Escaping the Productivity Trap<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/the-end-of-everything#escaping-the-productivity-trap" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Escaping the Productivity Trap" title="Direct link to Escaping the Productivity Trap">​</a></h2>
<p>I fell into the productivity trap of thinking the problem with my life and how I was going about it was about not managing the 50 million things I was trying to do properly with Todoist and Notion planners, reminders and alarms — I was looking at how to post three different social media brands efficiently and effectively, instead of maybe, not doing any of that instead.</p>
<p>The infamous "just because you can, doesn't mean you have to" adage; this 50 million things to achieve was again conforming to expectations, external expectations of who<em>I should be</em>and what I should achieve, to be valuable to society, to my friends and family, and to myself as a person.</p>
<p>But the cycles around the sun bring with them, hopefully, a breaking down of those beliefs — old beliefs that hang on ghosts of previous seasons, of previous cycles, previous personas and environments that produced not only the belief and the goal, but the person who would pursue them.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="breaking-free-from-clone-life">Breaking Free from Clone Life<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/the-end-of-everything#breaking-free-from-clone-life" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Breaking Free from Clone Life" title="Direct link to Breaking Free from Clone Life">​</a></h2>
<p>I do find myself conforming less.</p>
<p>Not that I was a big conformer — for the right price or opportunity, I wore the cliché smart-casual tech attire of jeans, business shirt and v-neck cashmere sweater.</p>
<p>Absolute clone-wear.</p>
<p>One example is when I was looking into how to turn my online time into something that actually pays my mortgage. I researched the most effective ways of having a personal brand across social media, and the posting cycles and branding required was a pathway I started down, to do<strong>gestures at all this</strong>efficiently so I could fit it into the 50 million thing agenda.</p>
<p>I followed the formula, the "best practices", the techniques, the strategies… like my clone-wear, I figured, it's the price to pay to get the thing right?</p>
<p>But seriously, what's "the thing"?</p>
<p>And why am I being a clone of all the other twats trying to be someone else, and not being myself, to whatever end that takes me?</p>
<p>I'm moving away from the clone life…</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-uncommon-path-forward">The Uncommon Path Forward<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/the-end-of-everything#the-uncommon-path-forward" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Uncommon Path Forward" title="Direct link to The Uncommon Path Forward">​</a></h2>
<p>Now, you'll see my "The Uncommon Engineer" persona…</p>
<p>…complete with dystopian avatar, anime-style branding and a corner of the internet I mean to cultivate for the specific types that resonate with me as I am — not an anime character obviously, but especially not as a dinner jacket and jeans-wearing tech-bro with a slick haircut.</p>
<p>The clone handbook told me I needed my personal name and goofy smiling photo across all my socials- why?</p>
<p>To appeal to everyone? I think I'll just find my audience of smart weirdos who like the same shit I do, and be happy with that.</p>
<p>The funny thing is I do mean to do business, as an AI tech company (more on this another time), as I am — this probably won't fit in with the Silicon Valley vibe, and that's fine.</p>
<p>My goal for life is to do what I love doing — learning and working with tech, building things, empowering the under-represented and making a living from it.</p>
<p>I know I have to let go of old expectations, fears and beliefs to get to that, but that's where I'm heading.</p>
<p>I told my wife this plan, and the first thing she asked me was "Does it make you happy?" (Yes I know happiness is not the pursuit of life, the conversation was more complex than this one question), and I said "yes" without hesitation.</p>
<p>The only thing that holds me back from this life is fear.</p>
<p>I'm not undecided, I'm just scared of letting go of what's familiar and safe.</p>
<p>But it needs to be done.</p>
<p>Have a great xmas and new years break to you, person reading this, and I'll see you in 2025.</p>
<p>Ron.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>AI-Sovereignty-Governance</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Knowledge Gap: Rethinking the Digital Divide for Pasifika]]></title>
            <link>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/knowledge-gap-rethinking-digital-divide-for-pasifika</link>
            <guid>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/knowledge-gap-rethinking-digital-divide-for-pasifika</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Argues digital divide for Pasifika is not device access but knowledge gap in using technology effectively for meaningful participation. Essential reading for un]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Talofa reader,</p>
<p>The "digital divide" is a term I've been hearing since I first got into community work with my charity back in 2017. Back then, researchers from the '90s had this simple way of looking at it - you either had computers and internet, or you didn't. Pretty straightforward stuff: get people devices, hook them up to the internet, problem solved. The lack of Pasifika representation in IT was wrapped up in this whole narrative.</p>
<p>But here's the thing - the research has come a long way since then. JAN A. G. M. Van Dijk's 2020 book "The Digital Divide" shows it's way more complex than just having a device and internet connection. Just because you've got the hardware doesn't mean you're actually participating in the digital economy in any meaningful way.</p>
<p>I didn’t really buy the whole "just get them devices" thinking. I knew it was an important step, for sure, but in my experience that device never made the techie.</p>
<p>So, after working in this space for a few years, something started nagging at me.</p>
<p>The real challenge facing Pasifika wasn't what everyone thought it was. And I knew this because it was exactly what had helped me succeed in tech myself.</p>
<p>But something wasn't adding up.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-device-paradox">The Device Paradox<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/knowledge-gap-rethinking-digital-divide-for-pasifika#the-device-paradox" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Device Paradox" title="Direct link to The Device Paradox">​</a></h2>
<p>Let's look at what's actually happening in the Pacific with devices and connectivity.</p>
<p>The numbers tell part of the story:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>By 2022, about 47% of people in the Pacific Islands had mobile subscriptions</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Only 27% were actually using mobile internet</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The networks technically cover 86% of the population</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Back in 2018, mobile subscription rates were sitting at 38%</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>So yeah, things are getting better. But we're still dealing with some major hurdles:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>The cost of devices and staying connected is still too high for many</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Building infrastructure across scattered islands isn't exactly straightforward</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Our small population means we don't get many service providers competing for business</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>A lot of our people still need help just using this stuff effectively</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>I tried digging up research on how all this device access was actually impacting our communities. What struck me wasn't what I found - it was what I didn't find. Almost nobody's studying this stuff properly. And you know how it goes - what you don't measure, you don't improve.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="a-closer-look-at-the-digital-divide-and-pasifika">A Closer Look at the "Digital Divide" and Pasifika<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/knowledge-gap-rethinking-digital-divide-for-pasifika#a-closer-look-at-the-digital-divide-and-pasifika" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to A Closer Look at the &quot;Digital Divide&quot; and Pasifika" title="Direct link to A Closer Look at the &quot;Digital Divide&quot; and Pasifika">​</a></h2>
<p>Van Dijk breaks this down into parts that really hit home when you think about our communities:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>It's not just about having a device - it's about having the right tools and being able to keep them running</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The way society's set up means resources aren't spread evenly</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Money and education play huge roles</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>There's this whole other level about actually knowing how to use tech effectively</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>And it matters who you've got around you who knows this stuff</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>The skills part really stands out to me. Van Dijk talks about two types:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>The basics of working with computers and managing your files (medium-related)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The deeper stuff - knowing how to search effectively, figure out what's legit information (content-related)</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>I see this play out all the time in my high school computer club. Here's a perfect example: I gave the students a challenge to look up what the number 42 meant, as it was the name of our class “Project 42”. Out of ten students, only one thought to use AI to find the answer. When I asked why, some hadn't even considered it, and others thought it would be cheating. That right there shows you how understanding tech - or misunderstanding it - creates its own kind of divide, even when everyone's got access to the same tools.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-second-level-divide">The Second-Level Divide<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/knowledge-gap-rethinking-digital-divide-for-pasifika#the-second-level-divide" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Second-Level Divide" title="Direct link to The Second-Level Divide">​</a></h2>
<p>Since my work focuses more on teaching people how to use tech rather than handing out hardware, I wanted to dig deeper into this "second-level divide" that Van Dijk talks about.</p>
<p>I went looking for data about how this plays out for Pasifika communities. There's not much out there - which tells you something right there about how much attention this gets. But I did find some interesting stuff with help from my friend Perplexity.ai.</p>
<p>Here's what the research shows about New Zealand:</p>
<p>The digital skills gap hits different groups differently, but guess who's often at the bottom of the stats? Our Pacific and Māori communities.</p>
<p>Not exactly breaking news aye.</p>
<p>Some other interesting bits:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>PISA data shows 27% of Māori students are online for more than 6 hours daily outside school - but what are they actually doing with that time?</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Having a phone with internet isn't the same as having proper access. Try coding on your phone and you'll see what I mean</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>When it comes to using government services online or doing business digitally, there's a clear gap between who can navigate these systems and who can't</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Our communities are more likely to get hit with computer viruses and online scams - probably because nobody's teaching digital street smarts</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>What really jumped out at me from all this wasn't the individual stats - it was the pattern.</p>
<p>Having tech isn't the same as knowing how to use it properly.</p>
<p>I've seen this firsthand with PTEC students, and it mirrors my own journey in tech. The thing that makes the real difference isn't having the flashiest device - it's knowing what to do with it.</p>
<p>Think about it this way: you can give someone a pro-level gaming PC, but that won't make them a software engineer. Just like having a fully kitted-out kitchen doesn't make you a chef.</p>
<p>What actually matters is the knowledge of how to use these tools.</p>
<p>In my own career, I didn't have better gear than anyone else - often had worse, actually. What made the difference was understanding how to learn, what to learn, and how to build on that knowledge effectively. That's what I call the knowledge accelerator effect.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-hidden-opportunity-in-ai">The Hidden Opportunity in AI<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/knowledge-gap-rethinking-digital-divide-for-pasifika#the-hidden-opportunity-in-ai" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Hidden Opportunity in AI" title="Direct link to The Hidden Opportunity in AI">​</a></h2>
<p>Here's where things get interesting for us Pasifika in today's tech landscape: we've got a chance to completely skip over the old "digital divide" story.</p>
<p>I keep saying this because it's important - AI is like having an always-on, ivy-league professor in your pocket. And I mean always:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>It's there 24/7</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Ready to answer questions or debate ideas</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Packed with knowledge about pretty much everything</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Can be your tutor, coach, or just someone to bounce ideas off</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Here's the thing people forget: our brains are still the best computers we've got. Regular computers and the internet weren't created to be smarter than us - they were made to help us learn and think better. The knowledge is what makes us smarter, not the device itself.</p>
<p>If we can tap into AI as a knowledge accelerator, our people can carry that learning power wherever we go.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-path-forward">The Path Forward<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/knowledge-gap-rethinking-digital-divide-for-pasifika#the-path-forward" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Path Forward" title="Direct link to The Path Forward">​</a></h2>
<p>The digital divide isn't about who's got the latest iPhone. It's about who knows how to make technology work for them. And that's actually good news for our Pasifika community, because it means we don't have to wait around for our device &amp; connectivity saviours to arrive.</p>
<p>We can start building our knowledge infrastructure right now. Here's what that looks like:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Creating learning platforms that work with how our people actually learn</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Building networks where knowledge gets shared through our communities</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Taking technical concepts and making them make sense in our cultural context</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Setting up mentoring that uses both human experience and AI smarts</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Focusing on making sure the knowledge is solid, not just making sure everyone has a device</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/knowledge-gap-rethinking-digital-divide-for-pasifika#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h2>
<p>The next chapter in digital inclusion isn't about getting more hardware into people's hands - it's about getting more knowledge into people's heads. As Pasifika, we've got a chance to show a different way forward, one that puts learning and knowledge-sharing at the centre.</p>
<p>This isn't just about closing some gap - it's about building our own bridges to where technology is heading. With AI and solid knowledge-building, we can create something that lasts, something that goes beyond just having access, to really transforming how our communities work with technology.</p>
<p>The future of Pasifika in technology isn't sitting in a device factory somewhere - it's in the knowledge we build and share with each other. By focusing on building strong knowledge networks and using AI to accelerate our learning, we can make sure our communities aren't just along for the ride in the digital future - we're helping to drive it.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading,</p>
<p>Ron.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>AI-Sovereignty-Governance</category>
            <category>pasifika</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What Happened to the Hackers?]]></title>
            <link>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/what-happened-to-the-hackers</link>
            <guid>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/what-happened-to-the-hackers</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Chronicles transformation of hacker culture from anti-establishment movement to corporate-commodified innovation theatre devoid of original rebellious spirit.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Talofa reader,</p>
<p>Up until my final year, I was on my way to joining the airforce after high school when one thing happened that changed it all in one night.</p>
<p>My Croatian friend and I were chatting on ICQ when he asked me if I wanted "to see something cool?"</p>
<p>Yes. Of course I did.</p>
<p>Then he "hacked" my Dad's computer that I was using.</p>
<p>I had one of those movie-moment revelations - you know the ones where the protagonist's eyes are suddenly opened to the real world and they transcend their mere mortal experience into god-mode. Maybe not quite that dramatic, but this was the beginning of an unstoppable journey into a world that would completely revolutionise how I saw and understood everything.</p>
<p>I discovered the world of the hacker.</p>
<p>At the time, I saw these uniquely smart, unapologetically irreverent, super creative and stubbornly anti-establishment minds who stood for more than just breaking into computers.</p>
<p>In my eyes, they represented freedom of information, freedom of expression, and true intellectual meritocracy - it didn't matter your age, gender, race, or background. If you loved computers, loved learning, and believed in a free and fair society, you were in.</p>
<p>These were the people willing to risk it all to give big corps and suits the middle finger.</p>
<p>And I was here for all of it.</p>
<p>Now it's 2024. The world is full of more injustice than ever, all the things hackers stood against are thriving, but that hacker world I came to idolise?</p>
<p>I can't find it anywhere.</p>
<p>What happened?</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-background">The Background<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/what-happened-to-the-hackers#the-background" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Background" title="Direct link to The Background">​</a></h2>
<p>To understand what we've lost, you need to understand what the hacker culture of the 90s and early 2000s was, at least to me.</p>
<p>It wasn't just about breaking into systems - it was a ethos, a way of life, a revolution in thinking.</p>
<p>My education didn't come from university lectures (I flunked out of my Bachelor of Computer Science). It came from downloading DOD "Rainbow Books" and Unix System V manuals, printing them out secretly at work. It came from late nights reading Phrack magazine, 2600, and even, The Anarchist Cookbook (controversial for some, sure) while trying to learn Linux on a cheap acer laptop.</p>
<p>I read stories about the Legion of Doom, watched "Hackers," "Sneakers," and "Takedown" on repeat.</p>
<p>The hacker ethos was about hands-on learning and questioning everything. We compiled our own kernels, learned to apply patches, debug kernel panics, and disassemble core dumps. Not because it would earn us certificates we could use for job interviews, but because we just needed to know how things worked.</p>
<p>The system wasn't just computers - it was society itself, how the world really worked, away from the mainstream media propaganda and Hollywood depictions of western civilisation verses the rest of the world..</p>
<p>We had real heroes too.</p>
<p>I know the community is at times divided in their opinion of these folks, but for meKevin Mitnickwasn't just a guy who social engineered his way into systems - he exposed how vulnerable our trust in authority was. People only know about "wikileaks"Julian Assange, but"mendax"was hacking the Pentagon and government systems, from Melbourne Australia, to challenge authority and expose corruption and government wrongdoing.Aaron Swartzfought for open access to academic knowledge until the system literally destroyed him.</p>
<p>These were people who were like "fuck it", and used this skill, and knowledge of technology to make an impact, make a difference.</p>
<p>And here's the thing: What does a teenage Samoan boy, growing up in New Zealand in the late 90s, have in common with these hackers?</p>
<p>Well, when you grow up on the margins of society, seeing the flaws in the system is usually what comes to you, and not you to it- what I found in hackers, and the hacker culture, other than an insatiable curiosity, was a drive to understand how things really were, and not just drinking whatever kool aid was convenient.</p>
<p>So, when they could see the inequity, the unfairness and bias of the system-<em>they could see me</em>.</p>
<p>The hacker ethos, to me, wasn't about chaos - it was about exposing truth and fighting for genuine fairness in an unfair world.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="death-by-a-thousand-cuts">Death By A Thousand Cuts<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/what-happened-to-the-hackers#death-by-a-thousand-cuts" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Death By A Thousand Cuts" title="Direct link to Death By A Thousand Cuts">​</a></h2>
<p>The following analysis isn't something I've pored over for days and weeks, but it literally aperplexity.aidriven "research" night I spent exploring what the fuck happened to the scene and the movement, that I saw in my youth.</p>
<p>Something fundamental has shifted in our relationship with technology and power. From all accounts, and book references from people who would know, the rebellious spirit of hacking hasn't died - it's been<em><strong>commodified</strong></em>and<em><strong>de-fanged</strong></em>under the guise of "innovation."</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-corporate-capture-of-hacker-culture">The Corporate Capture of Hacker Culture<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/what-happened-to-the-hackers#the-corporate-capture-of-hacker-culture" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Corporate Capture of Hacker Culture" title="Direct link to The Corporate Capture of Hacker Culture">​</a></h3>
<p>Remember when "hacker" meant someone who understood systems deeply enough to bend them to their will? Someone who'd spend countless hours understanding protocols, memory management, and system calls just to prove it could be done?</p>
<p>Like, just for the lulz and then moved on to something else?</p>
<p>Now we have "growth hackers" optimising click-through rates, "life hackers" selling productivity porn, and corporate "hackathons" where the biggest act of rebellion is staying up late to build another CRUD app to "help our customer solve problems"- just call it what it is, “help us help the customer, pay us more money.”</p>
<p>The same corporations hackers once targeted now brand themselves as hacker havens.</p>
<p>Facebook's "hack" culture appropriated the language<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/what-happened-to-the-hackers#footnote-1">1</a>while building the very walled gardens and surveillance systems we fought against. Google went from "don't be evil" to being the largest data harvester in human history. Even Microsoft, once the ultimate symbol of closed-source oppression and"embrace, extend, extinguish"tactics, now "loves" open source - while making sure they own the platforms it runs on.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="from-revolution-to-resume-padding">From Revolution to Resume Padding<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/what-happened-to-the-hackers#from-revolution-to-resume-padding" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to From Revolution to Resume Padding" title="Direct link to From Revolution to Resume Padding">​</a></h3>
<p>Today's "ethical hackers" aren't picking locks, phreaking phones, or breaking into systems to expose corruption - they're getting CEH certifications and doing bug bounties for the same companies collecting and selling our data.</p>
<p>The tools that once symbolised digital freedom - like encryption and anonymity - are now just bullet points on corporate security frameworks.</p>
<p>“Privacy is dead, amirite?” smh.</p>
<p>What's the most confronting part of all this?</p>
<p>I look at my own journey - from printing out Unix manuals and learning assembly to understand buffer overflows, to becoming a Solutions Architect at AWS. I'm literally helping build the cloud infrastructure that's centralising the internet into the hands of a few mega-corps.</p>
<p>The irony isn't lost on me.</p>
<p>We've become the very thing we swore to disrupt, just with better hoodies and more stock options.</p>
<p>FML.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-death-of-digital-liberation">The Death of Digital Liberation<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/what-happened-to-the-hackers#the-death-of-digital-liberation" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Death of Digital Liberation" title="Direct link to The Death of Digital Liberation">​</a></h3>
<p>The early hacker movement believed technology could democratise power.</p>
<p>We thought the internet would break down barriers and create a more equitable world. BBS systems and IRC channels were our autonomous zones, free from corporate and government control.</p>
<p>Instead, we've built systems of control more effective than anything before. The same encryption that was supposed to protect individual privacy now locks users into Apple's ecosystem. The open source movement that was meant to free software from corporate control is now primarily maintained by Google, Microsoft, and Facebook.</p>
<p>Even Linux, our symbol of freedom, is now mostly developed by corporate employees, and RedHat 5.2 was my very first Linux Distro.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-pasifika-perspective">The Pasifika Perspective<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/what-happened-to-the-hackers#the-pasifika-perspective" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Pasifika Perspective" title="Direct link to The Pasifika Perspective">​</a></h3>
<p>For me, as a Pasifika person, this hits different.</p>
<p>The hacker ethos appealed to me because it promised a way to challenge power structures from the outside. It wasn't about asking for permission or waiting for handouts - it was about taking control of technology and using it to gain knowledge, to empower us and give us the tools to control our own destiny.</p>
<p>But look at our digital world now - the same colonial patterns repeating themselves in new forms.</p>
<p>Big Tech's "solutions" for the Pacific often feel like digital colonialism: cloud services that make us dependent on foreign infrastructure, AI systems trained on our data but controlled by others, and "innovation hubs" that teach our people to be good corporate developers instead of digital revolutionaries.</p>
<p>The skills that once let us challenge power have become tools for maintaining it.</p>
<p>The hackers haven't disappeared - we've just been domesticated by the very systems we once sought to disrupt.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="not-dead-evolved">Not Dead, Evolved?<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/what-happened-to-the-hackers#not-dead-evolved" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Not Dead, Evolved?" title="Direct link to Not Dead, Evolved?">​</a></h2>
<p>Now, some will say hacker culture isn't dead - it's just evolved. They'll point to CTF competitions, the infosec community on Twitter/X/whatever the fuck Elmo calls it, and the occasional headline-grabbing hack. They'll talk about how "hacktivists" like Anonymous are still fighting the good fight.</p>
<p>But if we're honest, most CTFs have become recruiting grounds for three-letter agencies and tech giants. The same agencies and companies the original hackers were fighting against have turned hacking into a career path. Complete with certifications, HR-approved job descriptions, and corporate policies.</p>
<p>Others might argue that the corporatisation of hacking is a good thing - it's "maturity" of the field. That working within the system is more effective than fighting it.</p>
<p>That we can "change things from the inside".</p>
<p>Get the actual, fuck out of here…</p>
<p>I mean, “I don't believe that's possible.”</p>
<p>I've been on the inside for a while now, and I'm not seeing much change.</p>
<p>Why would I?</p>
<p>When the most profitable thing comes from merely appearing to do good for humanity rather than<em>actually</em>doing it, you can bet your bottom dollar that the vast majority of companies will choose the lower-cost "good optics" every time.</p>
<p>If anything, we're helping build better cages, just with nicer views—and we have to be honest with ourselves about that.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/what-happened-to-the-hackers#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h2>
<p>So what happened to the hackers?</p>
<p>We grew up.</p>
<p>Got mortgages. Had kids. Started worrying about savings and retirement plans.</p>
<p>I’d like to think that the system didn't beat us - it absorbed us.</p>
<p>But that would be a lie.</p>
<p>I think it did beat us—into submission and into the suburbs, with our normalised lives inside the nice, beautiful cages we find ourselves in today.</p>
<p>But this can’t be the end of it: the conditions that created hacker culture haven't gone away. If anything, they've gotten worse. The concentration of power, the abuse of technology, the need for genuine digital liberation - it's all still there.</p>
<p>Maybe what we need isn't to resurrect the old hacker culture, but to ignite something new. Something that takes the original spirit - the curiosity, the rebelliousness, the dedication to freedom and truth - and adapts it for today's fights.</p>
<p>Because while our generation is all comfortable in our tech jobs, building cloud infrastructure and training AI models, the next generation is facing challenges we quite literally only imagined.</p>
<p>Digital surveillance is normalised. AI is concentrating power even further into corporate hands. And the promise of technology as a liberating force feels further away than ever.</p>
<p>The real question isn't*"what happened to the hackers?"<em>It's</em>*"who will be the hackers we need now?"**</p>
<p>Maybe it's time for some of us old heads to remember what drew us to hacking in the first place.</p>
<p>Not the technical challenges, though those were fun.</p>
<p>But the belief that technology should serve freedom, not control. That knowledge shouldn't be locked behind paywalls.</p>
<p>That systems are meant to be understood, questioned, and when necessary, disrupted or destroyed.</p>
<p>Or maybe I'm just getting nostalgic in my old age.</p>
<p>Either way, I miss the hackers we used to be.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading,</p>
<p>Ron.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>AI-Security-Exploitation</category>
            <category>hacker-culture</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Burden of Knowing: Navigating Life in a System Built on Inequality]]></title>
            <link>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/burden-of-knowing-navigating-life-in-system-built</link>
            <guid>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/burden-of-knowing-navigating-life-in-system-built</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Examines Palestine genocide exposing Western hypocrisy and imperial order while reflecting on living within fundamentally unjust systems. Essential reading for ]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Talofa reader,</p>
<p>Get ready for a long rant, with a lot of swear words.</p>
<p>I started writing this piece after reading about the Israeliterrorist attackon Lebanon on Tuesday 17th September, that exploded hundreds of pagers across Lebanon and Syria, killing 12 and wounding<em>thousands</em>.</p>
<p>It had been 12 months already of the genocide of the Palestinian people by US-backed Israel, and now a blatant terrorist attack in two more Arab countries, and all I’m seeing is the sustained and morally bankrupt western media, continue it’s agenda of lies and propaganda, straight down the camera, for the world to see.</p>
<p>To watch the western world - politicians, media, pundits, public figures etc. - with a straight face, talk the most absolute bollocks I've ever heard in my entire life, has been quite a thing.</p>
<p>Watching Matt Miller, U.S. spokesperson, repeatedly claim that theU.S. had not found any evidence of Israel violating International Humanitarian Law, even after all videos we’ve seen, and evidence and testimony has stacked up on news sites, has been sickening.</p>
<p>There’s a ghoulishness to how these people lie remorselessly to cover for war crime after war crime, documented for the world to see.</p>
<p>If a real person lied to my face as much as western media and personalities have done in the last year or so, I'd have done what my younger brothers did when they caught up to a guy in high school who did the same shit-talking online.</p>
<p>But that kind of justice seems like it will never happen here.</p>
<p>I've always known underneath all of these rules, laws, norms and "democracy", it was a fraud or cover for (brace yourself) 'white supremacy' - not the lynching black folks kind, but the insidious "everyone play nice so we can maximise legal ways to exert supremacy without the mess, if we can help it" kind that maintains global inequities under the guise of civility and order.</p>
<p>But now, they can't keep it from getting messy.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="a-harsh-reawakening">A Harsh (Re)Awakening<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/burden-of-knowing-navigating-life-in-system-built#a-harsh-reawakening" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to A Harsh (Re)Awakening" title="Direct link to A Harsh (Re)Awakening">​</a></h2>
<p>I’ve always known the system was, “not good”.</p>
<p>It wasn't until I listened in on a few of the press conferences recently and watched the U.S. spokespeople dodge, deny and repeat propaganda talking points, to increasingly depraved Israeli war crimes, all captured on video, that I knew that it was all fucked.</p>
<p>The mask is well and truly off.</p>
<p>White supremacy is so baked into western society, we've had to actually delude ourselves into believing the lie that is democracy so that we can get along, but once you peel back all the layers, as has been done on the international stage, we've watched it trickle down into our newspapers and even our government's stance on the genocide.</p>
<p>Should we wait until the U.S. tells us an Arab baby's life is as valuable as a white<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/burden-of-knowing-navigating-life-in-system-built#footnote-1">1</a>baby's life, before<em>we</em>can say it?</p>
<p>I know the Crown has its own history of crimes against Māori in New Zealand history (they also did Samoa dirty) so I genuinely don't expect much from the NZ Government, but it is genuinely throw-up-levels of pathetic, watching us fawn over being the U.S.fluffer, like a good little cuck country with a submission fetish.</p>
<p>Yeah, this shit pisses me off, but these events over the last 12 months have just made me think about this reality of the challenge of living within a system you recognise as fundamentally unjust.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-illusion-unveiled">The Illusion Unveiled<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/burden-of-knowing-navigating-life-in-system-built#the-illusion-unveiled" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Illusion Unveiled" title="Direct link to The Illusion Unveiled">​</a></h2>
<p>It's been 12 months of this gaslighting, where we've watched the highest levels of international authority and governance, the ICJ and ICC, the UN and UN Security Council, really show us that there is no international law, there is no world order - just the empire's order and what it allows or doesn't allow.</p>
<p>The puppets and the theatre are finally beyond the pale (again)<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/burden-of-knowing-navigating-life-in-system-built#footnote-2">2</a></p>
<p>It's not that I didn't know a level of this propaganda, misinformation and disinformation has always been part of the media in western culture<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/burden-of-knowing-navigating-life-in-system-built#footnote-3">3</a>.</p>
<p>The historical context of this kind of propaganda has its roots (obviously) in colonialism and imperialism. African countries always portrayed as "dark" or "uncivilised" in 19th and early 20th century Western literature and media, which was used to justify colonial expansion and the"civilising mission", a political rationale for military invasion of African countries.</p>
<p>Western media will present biased or simplified views of complex situations in other countries e.g. the disproportionate focus on violence and poverty in Haiti, while completely overlooking theU.S. history of military occupationand politicalassassinationsin the country.</p>
<p>Western media then teamed up with political discourse in the west to exaggerate Iraq's weapons capability in the bullshit that was "Weapons of Mass Destruction", and how we all ate it up hook, line and sinker and paraded western invaders right into that country to murder its citizens, lay waste to cities, and then occupy, terrorise and torture the Iraqi people (Abu Ghraibanyone?).</p>
<p>None of these are even controversial!</p>
<p>It's in the history books (i.e. Wikipedia). There are photos and a whole wave of retrospective articles and analyses about how bad it was, after the fact, to say "oopsie, my bad" about it all.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-terrorist-state-of-israel">The Terrorist State of Israel<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/burden-of-knowing-navigating-life-in-system-built#the-terrorist-state-of-israel" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Terrorist State of Israel" title="Direct link to The Terrorist State of Israel">​</a></h2>
<p>Apparently, however, that (points to sub-heading) is controversial to say, today.</p>
<p>Maybe it's just the age I'm at, or the fact I've lived long enough to finally understand everything and see it for what it is, that the latest incident of Israel violating yet again, international and humanitarian law, that I just can't go back, mentally to the world how it was before.</p>
<p>Ignorant bliss.</p>
<p>It's been 12 months of genocide against the Palestinian people, and I've watched every western country (bar a few, shot Spain, Ireland, Belgium) tell us themass graves, thebombed hospitals, thesniped babies, theICU rotting babies, thetorture camps, theraped until they were dead prisoner, therefugee tent bombings, theburning families alive, thechildren bombed to pieces, andfamily members' remains gathered up in plastic bags- either didn't happen, as we watched the videos or live streams, or that it was justified as defence, even though Israel is an occupying state.</p>
<p>The other week thousands of pagers blew up hundreds of people in Lebanon - and the same western countries don't want to call it terrorism!</p>
<p>Every spokesperson, political figure and western media outlet has bent so far backwards in apologising and cowing for not only Israel, but the complicity of every western nation still sending arms and trading with the terrorist state of Israel, long after the ICC had ruled it was in violation of international law.</p>
<p>Countless headlines in papers and websites saying Palestinians were "dying", but Israeli Occupation Forces were being "killed". Mysterious outbreaks of famine and disease, but the papers were at a loss to know who was causing these things, they just seem to be magically happening to the Palestinians.</p>
<p>There were airstrikes that were killing Palestinians taking refuge in tents, and buildings, but no one seemed to know whose planes these were? The headlines were equally clueless, it really was a mystery.</p>
<p>But every utterance of "Health Department" had the very explicit "Hamas run" prefix, branded solidly on every headline.</p>
<p>Every one, bar none.</p>
<p>The media had no clue who was dropping the 2000 lb bombs on tent cities in Gaza, but were somehow always 100% confident of every Hamas or Palestinian fingerprint on all the atrocious crimes like... throwing rocks at their occupiers, or not getting out of the way when Israeli settlers turned up to evict you and your family and help themselves to your family home.</p>
<p>The answers during press time with Matthew Miller, the official spokesperson for the State Department, and<strong>Vedant Patel</strong>, who currently serves as the<strong>Principal Deputy Spokesperson</strong>for the U.S. Department of State, have been particularly mind-blowing in watching the western propaganda machines' spokespeople weasel and "lawyer" the English language out of any integrity of what any word means.</p>
<p>Western media and its spokespeople bullshit and gaslit so much it was pretty much its own language.</p>
<p>The list goes on, it's been 12 months of this bullshit, and anyone with any level of humanity can see it for what it is - absolute hypocrisy, blatant disinformation, disregard for international and humanitarian law, and the mostly unchallenged belief that these Zionists are the chosen and superior people.</p>
<p>You mean to tell me the terrorist state, on the American titty to the tune of Billions and Billions of dollars, committing war crimes since its inception, who believe that raping non-Jews is not really rape, and harbour the western world's paedophiles and sex traffickers…</p>
<p>…are the superior race?</p>
<p><em>Have you lot gone spare?</em></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="whats-the-point">What’s the Point?<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/burden-of-knowing-navigating-life-in-system-built#whats-the-point" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What’s the Point?" title="Direct link to What’s the Point?">​</a></h2>
<p>Here's the thing: this whole section of information, at this point in life, "is what it is". Every time I have to think about it—in this instance, while crafting this piece—it rightly pisses me off.</p>
<p>But that's just the way the world is right now. There's nothing I can do about it, at least not on that scale.</p>
<p>The real crux of writing this is what comes next. Yes, everything I've written above is just how the world is: western hypocrisy, white supremacy, imperialism, the treatment of the Global South as perpetually "less than" the Global North.</p>
<p>If that's just how the world is, how are we supposed to live with it?</p>
<p>Especially those of us who are from the Global South and, evidently, not white?</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-weight-of-knowledge">The Weight of Knowledge<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/burden-of-knowing-navigating-life-in-system-built#the-weight-of-knowledge" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Weight of Knowledge" title="Direct link to The Weight of Knowledge">​</a></h2>
<p>What do you do with that knowledge?</p>
<p>With that<em>knowing</em>?</p>
<p>It's hard to ignore the fact once it dawns on you: you're participating in a system that is flawed and not in your favour.</p>
<p>I guess it's not too different from living in New Zealand as a Samoan man.</p>
<p>You basically live multiple identities: one as a Samoan person with that worldview and values, the other as "whoever NZ society is comfortable with in that moment."</p>
<p>And I do mean, "What version of Samoan man are you comfortable with?"</p>
<p>Is banter acceptable?</p>
<p>What if I question you right back?</p>
<p>Would quiet and smiley be more to your liking?</p>
<p>The mechanism for fitting into a contrasting environment is to adapt, to change yourself.</p>
<p>Therein lies the dilemma (and the mental illness) of living somewhere you have to construct a persona.</p>
<p>You do this in order to "play along" with everyone else joking about thousands of pagers blowing up, affecting medical staff, children, and people going about their day.</p>
<p>The only "opt out" button is when we're safely back home. There, we don't have to tiptoe around the majority demographics' philosophies and beliefs to avoid becoming a target, being "identified" as difficult, or making things "awkward" for the group.</p>
<p>Everyone knows about microaggressions, code switching, and all that good stuff. That's all "cause" - the<em>effect</em>is constantly remaining vigilant. Not to the question "What is good and right?" because that would be easy and natural, but "What is good and right, according to these people?"</p>
<p>The "effect" of living like this is the emotional toll. It is exhausting.</p>
<p>Sure, we could solve or at least alleviate this by going full cognitive dissonance - but again, that's mental illness.</p>
<p>Secondly, why the fuck do we (or anyone for that matter) have to do this?</p>
<p>Why can't we all just agree that killing children, no matter whose children, is<em><strong>bad</strong></em>actually?</p>
<p>Why can't we all agree that anyone who says*"they're all terrorists, even the babies"*is actually fucked in the head?</p>
<p>You would<em><strong>think</strong></em>this would be a no-brainer.</p>
<p>When something has been documented so much, with scores of experts, scholars, and eyewitness accounts, and that knowledge is available for everyone to educate themselves on, you would need a lot of wilful ignorance to absolve yourself of knowing what's going on. Or worse, if you do know, to be transparent about why you choose the propaganda over the facts.</p>
<p>I think we would all be burdened with the knowledge, the<em><strong>knowing</strong></em>.</p>
<p>I think people who choose to "not know" either deliberately or by cognitive dissonance are doing so because they can't deal with the reality. Remember Mr. Reagan (aka Cypher) from The Matrix, who betrays everyone so he can be plugged back into the Matrix? People who avoid this knowledge because deep down they don't want to deal with it are a bit like Cypher. They would rather be blissfully ignorant than have to carry the burden of knowing.</p>
<p>What do we do to get through this?</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="strategies-for-survival-and-resistance">Strategies for Survival and Resistance<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/burden-of-knowing-navigating-life-in-system-built#strategies-for-survival-and-resistance" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Strategies for Survival and Resistance" title="Direct link to Strategies for Survival and Resistance">​</a></h2>
<p>Often when I'm overloaded with news of utter injustice and unchecked depravity going on one-sided in the world, I have to consciously take a step back, mentally and physically, from that stark reality. It's like unplugging from the matrix, so to speak.</p>
<p>Just because this is true, and this is reality, doesn't mean you have to stand and face the fire-hose 24/7. It doesn't help anyone to burn out, to despair and lose hope about the future. Sure, it doesn't help disassociating and living in la-la land either, imagining these things aren't real.</p>
<p>So how do we survive?</p>
<p>If you're Pasifika, you already know how to "go along to get along" in the face of the mainstream culture and value system. You know how to don the persona that allows you to blend in and not stand out as different. So the weight of knowledge that there is a terrible injustice happening in Palestine, and the Zionist world order is exposing western society and values for the fraud that it is - as a Pasifika person, it'll be the same playbook.</p>
<p>First, you want to carefully pick your battles. You don't have to be all things to everyone; you just have to make sure you and yours are safe and taken care of.</p>
<p>You'd do well to build and maintain your community connections, through which you can decompress and be reminded you're not experiencing this reality alone. It helps you have a safe space to just say how things really are for you, without having to explain it to folks who could never see your point of view and reasoning.</p>
<p>The group can do a lot for you, but it can only do so much. The rest of the survival and resistance comes from self-care and setting boundaries. You don't have to explain shit to anyone, but you do have to take responsibility for your boundaries and always enforce them.</p>
<p>Everything you do beyond this point is bonus.</p>
<p>You want to show solidarity with the cause? Protests and marches, writing online and flying the Palestinian flag, have at it - but understand what these evil shameless bastards are capable of, and there is no low they will not sink to.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="envisioning-a-different-future">Envisioning a Different Future<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/burden-of-knowing-navigating-life-in-system-built#envisioning-a-different-future" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Envisioning a Different Future" title="Direct link to Envisioning a Different Future">​</a></h2>
<p>I would like to think of the future with hope.</p>
<p>I imagine we would see new social structures far beyond the current white supremacy that exists today. I even consider how this phrase, "white supremacy," might sound to white people.</p>
<p>I know a fair few white people who have expressed the sentiment, "Where's my white privilege? Has it kicked in yet?" This basically shows me they have no clue what "white privilege" actually means. They would rather reject the idea outright than try to understand it. This is what the dominant culture does when faced with criticism or feedback - reject it if it threatens their superiority.</p>
<p>We have to re-imagine a future social structure where the "superior" of the species is the one that takes care of the most people. The superior race would be those who fight for everyone's right to shelter, food, education, and healthcare.</p>
<p>Like, how truly superior would that be!</p>
<p>I do believe the role of indigenous people and indigenous knowledge is one of bringing the human race back to its humanity. We need systems built on indigenous values and traditions of community, of looking after our planet, the animal kingdom, and each other.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="conclusion-the-struggle-continues">Conclusion: The Struggle Continues<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/burden-of-knowing-navigating-life-in-system-built#conclusion-the-struggle-continues" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion: The Struggle Continues" title="Direct link to Conclusion: The Struggle Continues">​</a></h2>
<p>I think what does my head in so much about this reality is that there's no resource or justice for it.</p>
<p>Israel's actions against Palestine, and now Lebanon, Syria, etc., is like the "boy with an influential family getting away with raping multiple women" analogy for me.</p>
<p>The public is in the courtroom hearing how it's the women's fault this is happening. They're told that the boy either didn't do it, or did it and didn't mean to, or that she was actually asking for it and the boy was entitled to do it.</p>
<p>This is where I've felt this sickening, enraging feeling before.</p>
<p>Having to listen to these kinds of bold-faced lies. To allow a pervert, an absolute piece of shit of society, say them and get away with it.</p>
<p>All because the "system" we're in says, "All of these rules and punishments for thee, but not for me".</p>
<p>How do we get there? I don't know.</p>
<p>This essay was a big rant about the state of the world right now. The international rules-based order and humanitarian law are falling. The carnage in terms of values and principles that we all held so high in western society is pretty much all down the toilet.</p>
<p>There's no coming back from what's been done.</p>
<p>We can't un-see and un-experience the depravity of Israel, the U.S., and Europe in genociding the Palestinians. It's been live-streamed and documented, one gruesome blown-up child after another.</p>
<p>We carry on, but the weight of knowing how things are is heavy. The pain that exists in the world that we see every day on our screens is overwhelming<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/burden-of-knowing-navigating-life-in-system-built#footnote-4">4</a>.</p>
<p>We would do well to take good care of ourselves in the meantime.</p>
<p>I don't have a good conclusion. I could rant on forever. When you can see your own child in the faces and pain of the children of Palestine, I think you'd want to rant about this injustice forever too.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading,</p>
<p>🇵🇸 "From the river to the sea, Palestine will be free"</p>
<p>P.s. Fuck every Zionist shit-bag and the systems that support them.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>AI-Sovereignty-Governance</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Beyond Netflix: The Critical Need for AI Literacy Among Indigenous Tech Leaders]]></title>
            <link>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/beyond-netflix-critical-need-for-ai-literacy-among</link>
            <guid>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/beyond-netflix-critical-need-for-ai-literacy-among</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Criticizes indigenous AI entrepreneur learning AI basics from Netflix after launch exposing dangerous lack of AI literacy among indigenous tech leaders.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Talofa reader,</p>
<p>I saw a post by a Māori Entrepreneur &amp; Investor who had recently launched an AI company, which left me flabbergasted.</p>
<p>In the post, he advises his followers to watch a documentary on Netflix, where the first episode discusses AI. He then remarks on the things he learned from this documentary, on Netflix, in September 2024.</p>
<p>This individual was surprised to learn about the extensive data requirements of large language models like ChatGPT. He only just discovered that these AI systems are trained on massive amounts of internet data, encompassing a wide variety of content. This includes not only openly available information but also potentially copyrighted material, and it's not clear how much of each was used.</p>
<p>The person emphasised that the training data for these models isn't limited to formal publications or books. Training datasets also absorbed personal content such as blog posts and social media interactions. As a result, these AI systems are exposed to a broad spectrum of human expression, which most likely included indigenous knowledge.</p>
<p>He's only just learned this, two weeks after launching his AI company that weaves AI with Indigenous knowledge.</p>
<p>I had to sit there, staring at the screen doing the "beautiful mind" meme, trying to make sense of the world.</p>
<p>How?</p>
<p>How are people that far along the AI investment and implementation path, especially Māori or Indigenous people, and they don't know the very first thing about the technology they're using?</p>
<p>This is the type of thing I'm seeing more of, and if indigenous values are actually important to people who claim they are, and they're more important than money, then this is a troubling trend of a lack of AI literacy amongst indigenous tech leaders, and it needs to be addressed.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="intersection-of-ai--indigenous">Intersection of AI &amp; Indigenous<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/beyond-netflix-critical-need-for-ai-literacy-among#intersection-of-ai--indigenous" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Intersection of AI &amp; Indigenous" title="Direct link to Intersection of AI &amp; Indigenous">​</a></h2>
<p>What this person has learned from this documentary is what everyone who works with and studies the literature of LLMs has known for some time. AI systems, particularly large language models, ingest vast amounts of data from across the globe, which inevitably incorporates traditional wisdom, cultural practices, and unique perspectives from indigenous communities, i.e., the blogs, newspapers, and online writings from those communities.</p>
<p>While the main talking points I've seen a lot lately when it comes to AI and Indigenous communities have been language preservation and revitalisation, the risk, which is always, always on the table with this, is the misappropriation or misrepresentation of this information without proper context or consent.</p>
<p>Have you solved for that, indigenous folks?</p>
<p>So, understanding the far-reaching impact of AI is crucial, as these technologies can influence how indigenous knowledge is perceived, used, and potentially commercialised on a global scale.</p>
<p>And maybe that's my gripe right there - that it's our own people commercialising indigenous knowledge, but not doing the due diligence to be good stewards and custodians of that knowledge.</p>
<p>What's the solution?</p>
<p>AI literacy training, or something.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="ai-literacy-for-indigenous-tech-leaders">AI Literacy for Indigenous Tech Leaders<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/beyond-netflix-critical-need-for-ai-literacy-among#ai-literacy-for-indigenous-tech-leaders" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to AI Literacy for Indigenous Tech Leaders" title="Direct link to AI Literacy for Indigenous Tech Leaders">​</a></h2>
<p>If that person's post is an example of where indigenous tech leaders are with AI literacy, we're in big trouble.</p>
<p>It's troubling enough to see someone relying on mainstream entertainment as a source of education; however, what's more concerning is the possible lack of comprehensive understanding about AI as a whole in indigenous tech circles.</p>
<p>To be clear, AI literacy goes way beyond knowing how to prompt an AI to build an app or generate an image. True AI literacy for indigenous tech leaders encompasses a deep understanding of the full spectrum of AI's impact within the indigenous context. This includes:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p><strong>Ethical Considerations</strong>: Understanding the potential for AI to perpetuate biases or misrepresent indigenous cultures.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Data Sovereignty</strong>: Recognising the importance of protecting and controlling indigenous data used in AI systems.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Cultural Preservation</strong>: Exploring how AI can be used to preserve and promote indigenous languages and traditions.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Economic Implications</strong>: Assessing how AI might affect indigenous economies and job markets.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Legal and Regulatory Landscape</strong>: Understanding the evolving legal framework surrounding AI and its implications for indigenous rights.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Technical Foundations</strong>: Grasping the basic principles of how AI systems work, including their limitations and potential.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Risk Assessment</strong>: Identifying potential risks of AI adoption and strategies for mitigation.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Opportunities for Innovation</strong>: Recognising how AI can be leveraged to address unique indigenous challenges and opportunities.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Indigenous tech leaders need to develop a nuanced understanding of AI's pros and cons, risks and opportunities, capabilities and limitations. This comprehensive knowledge is crucial for making informed decisions about AI adoption and development that align with indigenous values and interests.</p>
<p>Without this level of AI literacy, we're risking a lot.</p>
<p>Share## What's at Stake Here for Indigenous?</p>
<p>The impact of AI development and adoption for indigenous communities presents both massive opportunity and serious potential harms.</p>
<p>Uninformed or misinformed decision-making by tech leaders lacking a comprehensive understanding of AI's capabilities and limitations could lead to misguided strategies or implementations that fail to serve or even harm indigenous interests. This knowledge gap increases the risk of indigenous communities being left behind in the AI revolution or, worse, becoming unwitting fodder in systems that may exploit or misrepresent their cultural heritage.</p>
<p>Particularly concerning is the potential misuse or mishandling of indigenous knowledge within AI systems. Large language models, trained on massive amounts of internet data, may inadvertently incorporate sacred or sensitive indigenous information without proper context, consent, or respect for cultural protocols.</p>
<p>This could lead to the inappropriate dissemination of protected knowledge, cultural appropriation on a grand scale, or the distortion of traditional wisdom when filtered through AI algorithms.</p>
<p>Without informed leadership and careful oversight, AI technology inadvertently becomes a tool that perpetuates historical patterns of exploitation and marginalisation, rather than empowering indigenous communities in the digital age.</p>
<p>When indigenous folks only know about "Data Sovereignty" as the risk with LLMs, that potentially means that person doesn't understand LLMs and the AI topic well enough.</p>
<p>What are the risks and concerns that are already known about LLMs?</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="ai-ethical-concerns">AI Ethical Concerns<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/beyond-netflix-critical-need-for-ai-literacy-among#ai-ethical-concerns" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to AI Ethical Concerns" title="Direct link to AI Ethical Concerns">​</a></h2>
<p>I was actually in the middle of researching the positive and negative effects of relying on AI for research and learning when I read the LinkedIn post that this post drew inspiration from.</p>
<p>The paper I was reading,"The effects of over-reliance on AI dialogue systems on students' cognitive abilities: a systematic review", had this brilliantly summarised list of ethical concerns with respect to AI.</p>
<p>The key points are:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>AI hallucinations</strong>: Generation of inaccurate or misleading information</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Algorithmic biases</strong>: Potential to perpetuate or amplify existing societal prejudices</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Plagiarism</strong>: Reproduction of content without proper attribution</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Privacy concerns</strong>: Issues related to accessing and processing vast amounts of personal data</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Transparency issues</strong>: Lack of clarity in AI decision-making processes</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Ethical implications</strong>: Need for responsible development and deployment of AI technologies</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>These points represent widely known AI ethical risks that any tech leader, including those in indigenous communities, should be familiar with to make informed decisions about AI adoption and development.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/beyond-netflix-critical-need-for-ai-literacy-among#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h2>
<p>In conclusion, the intersection of AI and indigenous knowledge presents both unprecedented opportunities and serious challenges.</p>
<p>The apparent lack of comprehensive AI literacy among some indigenous tech leaders is concerning and needs urgent attention. This knowledge gap, in my humble opinion, exposes communities and indigenous knowledge to massive risk of exploitation and misrepresentation.</p>
<p>Moving forward, it is super critical that indigenous tech leaders prioritise developing a nuanced understanding of AI technologies, their implications, and ethical considerations. This goes beyond surface-level knowledge of AI applications to gain a deep grasp of AI's potential impacts on everything to do with culture, data sovereignty, and community well-being.</p>
<p>Ultimately, the goal should be to empower indigenous tech leaders to become not hacks or basic implementers of AI, but informed, critical, and innovative players in the global AI landscape.</p>
<p>And you can't do that by learning AI basics from a Netflix documentary.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading, see you in the next one.</p>
<p>Ron.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>AI-Sovereignty-Governance</category>
            <category>indigenous-knowledge</category>
            <category>ai-literacy</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[There is no "Pasifika in Tech" Problem]]></title>
            <link>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/there-no-pasifika-in-tech-problem</link>
            <guid>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/there-no-pasifika-in-tech-problem</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Reframes Pasifika tech issue arguing problem is not low representation but manufactured false demand by nonprofits and corporations. Essential reading for under]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Talofa reader,</p>
<p>I had some thoughts recently on this topic, and after a live stream and discord discussion, wanted to note things down.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="misunderstanding-the-pasifika-in-tech-problem">Misunderstanding the “Pasifika in Tech” Problem<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/there-no-pasifika-in-tech-problem#misunderstanding-the-pasifika-in-tech-problem" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Misunderstanding the “Pasifika in Tech” Problem" title="Direct link to Misunderstanding the “Pasifika in Tech” Problem">​</a></h2>
<p>I remember reading this article in 2021, back when I was looking into why there are so few Pasifika in the tech industry.</p>
<p>This quote right at the top stands out:</p>
<p><em>“Stop repeating the conversation, start the action — you’re leaving us behind.” That’s an example of what the Department of Internal Affairs heard when it interviewed a number of Pacific peoples in 2020 to find out what they see as the barriers to digital inclusion.</em></p>
<p>This, and many other examples of stories at the time, convinced me there was a demand from our community for access to the tech industry and careers.</p>
<p>But after several years, trying various things in the community, with local councils and Pasifika churches, I'm not convinced this was ever the case.</p>
<p>A member of my Discord posed this question in the discussions forum:</p>
<p><em>"Do we have a Pasifika in Tech problem? What is the problem? Who is the problem for?"</em></p>
<p>This was a question I asked on theTechNesian Live Stream, and it's one I've been asking myself recently, especially in light of thePasifika Tech Network shutdown.</p>
<p>Back in 2021, I would have said "yes," but my answer today would be "No, we don't have a Pasifika in tech problem."</p>
<p><em>Why is that?</em></p>
<p>Because*"low numbers of Pasifika in tech"<em>is not the same as</em>"there are barriers and no support for getting more Pasifika in tech."*</p>
<p>One of these is a Pasifika problem, the other is just an objective statistic in the tech industry.</p>
<p>We got it wrong somewhere way back at the start.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="manufacturing-demand">Manufacturing Demand<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/there-no-pasifika-in-tech-problem#manufacturing-demand" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Manufacturing Demand" title="Direct link to Manufacturing Demand">​</a></h2>
<p>From about 2020 onwards, possibly amplified by the realities shown to us by the pandemic, there was a sudden narrative for getting more Pasifika into technology careers. We needed to help our community out of these jobs that saw them out delivering things in the middle of a pandemic because they had no choice.</p>
<p>The tech industry was going to be the choice that saved them.</p>
<p>I started seeing interviews and newspaper articles crop up. Established organisations were pumping out the Pasifika marketing for grad roles and being a great place to work for Pasifika. New organisations were popping up, marketing the Pasifika angle hard; imagery and themes on websites for these education providers and workplaces were exploding at this time.</p>
<p>The community was putting on Talanoa and evenings to talk about getting Pasifika into tech and how they were doing that<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/there-no-pasifika-in-tech-problem#footnote-1">1</a>.</p>
<p>I attended a few, and they were all well-attended.</p>
<p>I remember going to a "Tech Talanoa" out South Auckland once that had four panelists "working in tech," none of whom were engineers<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/there-no-pasifika-in-tech-problem#footnote-2">2</a>. One Pasifika father got so frustrated at one point from not hearing anything related to the technical side of the industry that he grabbed the microphone and, with broken English, told the panel that he brought his 16-year-old son there to hear about "the programming," and he hasn't heard anything yet.</p>
<p>I feel like these talks just bamboozled our community.</p>
<p>They gas-lit them into thinking:</p>
<p>a) "Oh, you don't have to like tech, just come and bring your vibes,"</p>
<p>and/or</p>
<p>b) "Hey, the technical side is hard; maybe just do your customer service role like a good 'soft skills worker.'"</p>
<p>I don't feel like these events did a great service to the community— too many times it was "come to tech on vibes and Pasifika-ness".</p>
<p>Don't get me wrong, I think there's a lot of value in indigenous knowledge and wisdom- but the key to the door the community was knocking on was a change in their economic situation, not a pep-talk for revolutionising a system that's got a long way to go before it puts profit aside for indigenous brownie points.</p>
<p>But I digress...</p>
<p>How could we<em>not</em>think "yo, there's crazy demand by Pasifika for getting into tech, where do we start solving for this?"</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="rethinking-the-problem-definition">Rethinking the Problem Definition<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/there-no-pasifika-in-tech-problem#rethinking-the-problem-definition" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Rethinking the Problem Definition" title="Direct link to Rethinking the Problem Definition">​</a></h2>
<p>When we all started trying to help get more "Pasifika into Tech," did we stop and ask a crucially important question—do Pasifika<em>want</em>to get into Tech?</p>
<p>I saw an example just this week of framing a problem in a way that may make an assumption that leads to the wrong pathway being taken, similar to how I feel the "Pasifika in tech" pathway was misunderstood.</p>
<p>This statement from a fairly prominent Māori scholar, who said:</p>
<p><em>"We need to ensure we create pathways for education in IT and in particular computer science, machine learning and all areas of AI. There are many reasons why, statistically, Māori make up about 5% of the tech industry and 0.16% of the AI workforce.<strong><strong>We just need to work on removing those barriers and making clear pathways</strong></strong>."</em></p>
<p>That last line, in bold.</p>
<p>This perspective underscores a critical need to differentiate between actual barriers—such as lack of access or education—and just a lack of interest in pursuing careers in these fields.</p>
<p>I'm not sure about everyone else, but when I noticed the lack of Pasifika in tech while contracting in the industry back in 2016, my next step was to ask "why?" The answers I found online were that it was a*"pipeline problem,"*i.e., Pasifika weren't being exposed to these options early in their school life, so they weren't picking it up at the tertiary or work end of things.</p>
<p>That's fair.</p>
<p>That's a long-tail investment that looks like code clubs for 8-12 year old Pasifika kids, exposing them to the tech option, and hoping that seed planted grows into a choice when they're looking at what to study at university.</p>
<p>Problem solved, case closed.</p>
<p>What about the Pasifika of working age now or in years 11, 12, and 13 of high school who need to make some choices soon?</p>
<p>If the “problem” definition is that Pasifika are in sun-setting industries, Pasifika are in mostly low-paid work, and Pasifika are underrepresented in the tech field (i.e., the field that’s going to determine a lot of the future workforce and decision-making, such as bias in tech design, AI, etc.), then yes, we have a***“Pasifika have a problem that getting into tech will help solve”***problem.</p>
<p>These are<em><strong>economic</strong></em>problems.</p>
<p>A tech career is not the only solution to this, any high paying job will help solve for this.</p>
<p><em>Why is this important?</em></p>
<p>Because then your audience, motivations and strategies are completely different- you now have someone who just wants to get in a better financial position, whether that's tech, real estate or multi-level marketing.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-challenge-of-assisting-the-uninterested">The Challenge of Assisting the Uninterested<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/there-no-pasifika-in-tech-problem#the-challenge-of-assisting-the-uninterested" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Challenge of Assisting the Uninterested" title="Direct link to The Challenge of Assisting the Uninterested">​</a></h2>
<p>This makes for a really different problem to solve, i.e., helping someone who knows they want to get into tech and you’re in a position to help them is relatively straightforward. Helping someone who doesn’t know what they want (tech) or wants something you can’t give them (carrying them into tech) is a waste of everyone’s time.</p>
<p>This would be my experience going into the community over the past several years, talking about tech careers, showing up to panels and doing the same- advocating for more Pasifika into tech. I worked with Samoan churches to deliver free, weekly coding &amp; technology sessions; and in each iteration of the community programme, even after a strong start, the interest and attendance would wane and decline to a point where it was not worth the effort by myself and my team to continue.</p>
<p>I truly believed the demand problem was because we "didn't know about tech careers", and solving that by taking the good word out into the community would be met with a fair share of the "great demand" there was for Pasifika wanting to get into tech, but just wasn't getting the support- the industry not meeting them where they were at.</p>
<p>Well, me and my team did meet the community where they were at- in schools, in churches etc.</p>
<p>Anyone can do a one-off big bang event and "do numbers" like a highlight reel.</p>
<p>Me and my team weren't interested in that.</p>
<p>We were here for the long-term week in and week out support and building up of the community's tech exposure, knowledge and capabilities.</p>
<p>And I feel like we did that, from 2017 with code clubs, taking a break during the pandemic, and coming back out into Pasifika churches and high schools when things opened up again.</p>
<p>The trouble with that is, it takes two to tango- and after getting "stood up" more than a few times on more than a few different initiatives, we have to read the feedback (at least for us) for what it is.</p>
<p>And when I see full-time organisations, dialling back down on the Pasifika in tech rhetoric, pivoting away from the original mission statement, especially given the number of staff they have available, I know it’s not just me.</p>
<p>For Pasifika, getting into tech is not "a problem", because it's not what they want, so not being in it, is not a problem.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="futility--an-inevitable-outcome">Futility &amp; An Inevitable Outcome<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/there-no-pasifika-in-tech-problem#futility--an-inevitable-outcome" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Futility &amp; An Inevitable Outcome" title="Direct link to Futility &amp; An Inevitable Outcome">​</a></h2>
<p>It took me way too long to accept that this was the case- there isn't a demand for Pasifika wanting to get into tech, that it wasn't a lack of knowledge i.e. even when they knew what was available, it just wasn't what a lot of Pasifika were interested in.</p>
<p>I was convinced early on that Pasifika “don’t know what they don’t know,” so I thought showing them the tech solution would be the thing to do. A lot of double talk and gestures without commitment helped confuse the reality, and it took too long for me to sort the signal from the bullshit—that’s on me, though.</p>
<p>I never had a problem with Pasifika not being interested in tech, I've said on every occasion, if this is you, great, if not, you'll find what you're into elsewhere, this isn't the be-all end-all for Pasifika futures- its just an option, for the geeks and the technically minded<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/there-no-pasifika-in-tech-problem#footnote-3">3</a>.</p>
<p>The issue here is when the problem is misunderstood, then the solution and efforts to solve the problem are actually irrelevant, ineffective, and largely a waste of everyone's time.</p>
<p>It's only happened recently, but I've started changing the way I engage with the "Pasifika in tech" landscape. It's not all the way "there" yet, but it's a work in progress.</p>
<p>Nowadays, I take a more “push” than “pull” approach. To take a tech concept that is, I put a signal out into the community, a sign-up, a survey. If that activity gets numbers, my team and I build for those respondents. We try to address the need, within our objectives and skill-sets, where it's at.</p>
<p>I set my expectation to low numbers and high quality, rather than filling seats with tyre kickers.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-rise-and-fall-of-pasifika-in-tech-initiatives">The Rise and Fall of "Pasifika in Tech" Initiatives<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/there-no-pasifika-in-tech-problem#the-rise-and-fall-of-pasifika-in-tech-initiatives" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Rise and Fall of &quot;Pasifika in Tech&quot; Initiatives" title="Direct link to The Rise and Fall of &quot;Pasifika in Tech&quot; Initiatives">​</a></h2>
<p>It's interesting to note where the industry is at this point in time.</p>
<p>Since 2020, fast forward four years, and it's a lot quieter now on the socials, on the marketing, and the push for "Pasifika in tech" has all but vanished from the scene. Organisations that were championing the cause of getting more "Pasifika in tech" have long since pivoted to other underrepresented groups, or change the focus from helping Pasifika get into tech directly, to helping Pasifika feel more at home in their own skin, then somewhere along the lines this will help them get into tech<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/there-no-pasifika-in-tech-problem#footnote-4">4</a>.</p>
<p>It's a new day, probably about time too- I know my draft of a piece titled*"Not Samoan enough for Samoans, and never going to be Palagi"*would be a good follow on from this discussion, but again, another story for another time.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading, more than happy to hear your thoughts on this? Do you agree? Disagree?</p>
<p>Ron.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>AI-Sovereignty-Governance</category>
            <category>pasifika</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Shutting Down the Pasifika Tech Network]]></title>
            <link>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/shutting-down-pasifika-tech-network</link>
            <guid>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/shutting-down-pasifika-tech-network</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Post-mortem analysis of failed Pasifika Tech Network showing pipeline not engagement problem is actual barrier to community participation. Essential reading for]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Talofa reader,</p>
<p>A few weeks ago, I made the relatively easy decision to wind down The Pasifika Tech Network.</p>
<p>"Failed project" may be a harsh way to put it, but I think there's value in calling something what it is, so you can better understand how <em>not</em> to do it again in future.</p>
<p>This is a project that failed.</p>
<p><em>Ok, but what did it fail to do? And why?</em></p>
<p>To understand that, we have to go back to the beginning and look at why it was created in the first place; what its intended goal was; and the reasons it wasn't able to live up to this.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="genesis-of-the-network">Genesis of the Network<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/shutting-down-pasifika-tech-network#genesis-of-the-network" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Genesis of the Network" title="Direct link to Genesis of the Network">​</a></h2>
<p>When I started on the "how do I get more Pasifika into tech?" journey back in 2016, my first stop was trying to identify Pasifika already in tech and creating a network so we could help each other into various roles in the industry.</p>
<p>I started the LinkedIn group known today as "Pasifika in IT" (originally called the "Polynesian Tech Professionals"), to gather said professionals, and was dismayed that of the 300+ people who joined the group, only a handful were technical, and only 2 showed up to a meetup.</p>
<p>Digging into the root of the problem, I discovered a*"pipeline issue"*.</p>
<p>I started running code clubs in 2017, and in 2019 "The Pasifika Tech Education Charity" was born, delivering code clubs and workshops for Pasifika primary through high school students to cater to the "pipeline".</p>
<p>The goal was always to get a direct line from Pasifika people to tech work and careers. With limited time and resources, I figured a focus on cultivating a network of Pasifika professionals would:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>Develop and advance Pasifika tech workers careers</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Those advanced tech workers would feed back into the code club volunteering for the next generation.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>The group was filled with sales people, marketers, recruiters, people managers and generally "rubber neckers". Trying to get engagement (I guess like most/all LinkedIn groups) was like pulling teeth, screaming into the void, or talking to a brick wall - you pick what euphemism works for you.</p>
<p>Bottom line, it was a group of spectators waiting for the show to start.</p>
<p>I eventually found two engineers who joined the group, brothers, who were actually technical and were the target demographic for this group (shout out to the Sauni brothers). Before the group became a complete ghost town, we enjoyed a couple of meetups where we had coffee, traded career stories, and ate cake.</p>
<p>As I redirected my time and effort to my kids' code club programme in the community, I eventually handed the group over to a good friend Steven Paea, and stood down from any and all Pasifika in IT things.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="2021-post-covid-a-new-hope">2021 Post-Covid: A New Hope<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/shutting-down-pasifika-tech-network#2021-post-covid-a-new-hope" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 2021 Post-Covid: A New Hope" title="Direct link to 2021 Post-Covid: A New Hope">​</a></h2>
<p>Fast forward to 2021, the world as we knew it was forever changed by the pandemic.</p>
<p>Everyone had finally experienced and seen with their own eyes, the disparity between communities and groups of people in terms of wealth, opportunities and real-life realities. Coming out of the lock-downs and the country really coming to grips with how fragile and unequal our society was, it felt like there was a new-found hope, and drive to get the "have nots" i.e. communities like Pasifika, the hell out of the enduring poverty-riddled situation it's always been in.</p>
<p>This was the new hope that had me hoping for maybe a new result to an old play - can I start up another Pasifika Network?</p>
<p>Well, I did.</p>
<p>And it was called "The Pasifika Tech Network" aka PTN... and it was pretty good at the start...</p>
<p>To be fair, it was more organised this time. It had a proper registration form, a mailing list system, a Discord server; we eventually had a newsletter, a website and a GitHub account.</p>
<p>I'm a 24/7 geek, so being pathologically online and around to cultivate and grow the online community aspect of our network wasn't anything out of the ordinary for me. I was online, starting conversations, sharing information, organising the server with new features, bots (with the help of Luka Tauvae), and taking feedback from members to create channels and events to support our mission.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-pasifika-tech-network-in-action">The Pasifika Tech Network in Action<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/shutting-down-pasifika-tech-network#the-pasifika-tech-network-in-action" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Pasifika Tech Network in Action" title="Direct link to The Pasifika Tech Network in Action">​</a></h2>
<p>The PTN was starting to pick up steam.</p>
<p>We had even formed a "committee" with a group of committed members, to meet once a month to discuss and plan things to make the server, and the network what we wanted it to be.</p>
<p>Over the next couple of years, the PTN ran regular online study sessions (complete with study bots, with timers, awards and task tracking), we had online meetups to catch-up with people who were around; we had several in-person meetups for both technical &amp; professional presentations, as well as just social gatherings for a drink, cake and even board games.</p>
<p>We ran a discussion forum on the Discord that went deep into members experiences, good and bad as well as things like salaries, racism and workplace bullying. We even had a health-and-wellbeing channel where everyone posted their workout goals, or just encouragement for staying physical given our industry is pretty sedentary.</p>
<p>Our careers channel posted job descriptions of roles going at members workplaces, and I'm happy to say more than a few members landed roles successfully through the network.</p>
<p>In an effort to try to recruit more members to active roles within the network, helping with the mission of "getting more Pasifika into tech", we setup a Volunteering system where members could pick the activity they wanted to volunteer on - events, writing the monthly newsletter, being a volunteer with my charity (PTEC), promo team.</p>
<p>There were so many comments and sentiments to the effect of "grateful for this space, there's nothing like it". I even put it to the discussion forum once, during one of many "quiet" periods in the network, whether we should open up to non-Pasifika to join as well?</p>
<p>I got a resounding "no, this is our space, we can let our guard down here like we can't anywhere else".</p>
<p>Verbally, and occasionally in-person, there was a lot of consensus that this was an important and needed space.</p>
<p>So, why did it go the way it went after all this?</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-signs-and-reality">The Signs and Reality<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/shutting-down-pasifika-tech-network#the-signs-and-reality" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Signs and Reality" title="Direct link to The Signs and Reality">​</a></h2>
<p>When the activities online required constant initiation by the same people every time, fewer people would be "online" and contribute to the chat, it definitely felt like the momentum and interest was waning. Surveys to better understand what could make the network more valuable, emailed to members got little to no responses. Even the volunteering channels with people joining activities as low-maintenance as the promo team i.e. the "write something about the network on your social media" activities team got zero posts out.</p>
<p>That's not to say no one did anything, a couple of people really came through with their time and efforts - Luka with the discord admin, GT with the Study sessions and Charity, TJ with the newsletter - but the general consensus kept pointing out that I may be barking up the wrong tree.</p>
<p>Was there really a demand for Pasifika badly wanting to get into tech, where they were crying out for a network like this to help get them there?</p>
<p>The reality of the demographic in the PTN wasn't the cliche poverty-stricken Pasifika, but that's not to say they weren't without their challenges. The folks the network was fostering were those who were already in tech, they'd done the hard work or caught the break already in their niche interest, and gotten into tech.</p>
<p>They had their own places, even if renting, they were on better salaries, and weren't struggling in the same way their parents were/did. Yes, still very much involved in family and community, so time, space and money is shared.</p>
<p>Members had young families, trying to live and survive in Auckland, some even moving out of Auckland for that reason. A lot of folks were still in the junior end of their careers, so they were in a building phase, which I know from experience, takes time and energy. You don't have the flexibility of a more seasoned tech worker, or the opportunities that allow for it.</p>
<p>You also don't have the knowledge, or experience to roadmap your way there, so you're stuck in this stage for longer if not indefinitely.</p>
<p>I would think this is exactly why Pasifika, in tech, would lean into a network like the one I was trying to build; because it would expedite the process of advancing themselves to a place with less stress and more resources, provide community where our people were scarce, and to be able to stand on the few shoulders of people available to support and bridge this gap.</p>
<p>I was wrong.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="lessons-learned">Lessons Learned<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/shutting-down-pasifika-tech-network#lessons-learned" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Lessons Learned" title="Direct link to Lessons Learned">​</a></h2>
<p>I was raised by my mum to always look at myself and my actions first—the "log out of your own eye" before the speck of dust in someone else's, so to speak.</p>
<p>So here are some things I've thought about that were in my control and contributed to the PTN not working out.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="underestimated-the-work-required">Underestimated the Work Required<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/shutting-down-pasifika-tech-network#underestimated-the-work-required" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Underestimated the Work Required" title="Direct link to Underestimated the Work Required">​</a></h3>
<p>To an extent, I had expectations that I would invest x amount of effort that would be picked up at point 'y'—you know, like a mathematical equation. If I had the right parameters and got the graph trending to the required threshold, nature would take over and it would organically grow on its own. It didn't, so I might have underestimated where that line was and subsequently never reached it. This would explain why I had to keep investing x amount of effort over the lifetime of the PTN without it ever taking off.</p>
<p>Maybe I was aware that more of me was required to take it further and find that threshold, but that's something I've been aware of doing this work.</p>
<p>I have a finite amount of time, effort, and fucks to give about any one thing in my life, and I knew that I would give what I had to for this, and no more.</p>
<p>If what I had to give, was less than what was required, and no-one else could make up the short-fall, this was always going to be the natural conclusion.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="misunderstood-the-demographic">Misunderstood the Demographic<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/shutting-down-pasifika-tech-network#misunderstood-the-demographic" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Misunderstood the Demographic" title="Direct link to Misunderstood the Demographic">​</a></h3>
<p>This is another reason I think it didn't work out.</p>
<p>I didn't understand the demographic I was targeting. I thought I did; I thought I knew their motivations, drive, and intrinsic values. Even when surveying and parsing that data, I thought I had things on track. But the proof was in the pudding—whatever I was doing was not the "thing" that was going to get the result I was after from this group.</p>
<p>Maybe they just wanted to hang out occasionally, leave their careers in the 9-5 slot, and just be part of something in the background.</p>
<p>Funnily enough, I sent out a post-closedown survey to get feedback on how people felt about the network and what did and didn't work. Surprisingly, I got a few responses saying they wished they had participated more, that they were just happy something like the PTN existed and they could join in whenever they wanted to.</p>
<p>What kind of member is that?!</p>
<p>What kind of member is happy for something to exist that they can benefit from when they feel like participating, and were then sad to see it go?</p>
<p>I know this and the "just hang out" demographic was not my intended audience, and misunderstanding what I was working with is on me.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="not-the-right-person">Not the Right Person<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/shutting-down-pasifika-tech-network#not-the-right-person" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Not the Right Person" title="Direct link to Not the Right Person">​</a></h3>
<p>At the risk of sounding like a self-fulfilling prophecy, one takeaway I have to consider—or know is a possibility—is that I wasn't the right person for this work.</p>
<p>All things being equal, let's say the work was roughly what I thought it would be, time and energy investment-wise, and the demographic was keen, driven, and ambitious Pasifika engineers looking for a place to belong to, contribute, and grow—was I the right person to lead and do this work of starting and growing the network?</p>
<p>I would say yes. Under these circumstances, I think I would be.</p>
<p>But circumstances outside of this? i.e., circumstances as they turned out to be, could have benefited from someone with different skills. Someone who could have inspired this demographic from where they were to where they needed to be for this vision to succeed.</p>
<p>This, I think, is my shortcoming, my failure. I wasn't the right person for solving this problem.</p>
<p>I'm the person who can take a junior engineer and show them the way to senior, and play the corporate tech industry game.</p>
<p>I'm just not the person to make you <em>want</em> that for yourself.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="know-when-to-fold-em">Know When to Fold ‘Em<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/shutting-down-pasifika-tech-network#know-when-to-fold-em" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Know When to Fold ‘Em" title="Direct link to Know When to Fold ‘Em">​</a></h3>
<p>I maybe made a few "new venture" mistakes here, as you can tell already by "not knowing the demographic," i.e., my market or "customers". I didn't do enough to validate my thesis that this was something people wanted. I assumed, based on what I thought would be valuable and what has been a valuable experience for me in my professional network, that it would be valuable for my Pasifika tech community too.</p>
<p>Failing this, and continuing with the thesis long after the signals were there that this wasn't the case, I could have probably wound it up sooner and saved some time and energy.</p>
<p>That's on me.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="next-steps">Next Steps<a href="https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/shutting-down-pasifika-tech-network#next-steps" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Next Steps" title="Direct link to Next Steps">​</a></h2>
<p>Where to from here?</p>
<p>I'd be lying if I said this wasn't disheartening. As much as I know I'm no one's saviour, it sucks to put energy into something that doesn't pan out. When it's something like work and career, that's one level of sucking. When it's a plan you think could have far-reaching benefits for your community and this was just the first step, it's even harder.</p>
<p>For me, I still have a charity that has been going for 5-6 years now, with Pasifika volunteers that fit the description of the demographic I was targeting with the PTN. I think I got it right in this case because we are going strong, with outcomes and activities in the community to validate that claim.</p>
<p>I think, going forward, I'm going to validate and prioritise what I'm going to dedicate time and energy to more ruthlessly. I think it's best not only for myself but for all the other things in my life that require time and energy—it would be unfair to spend it unwisely again.</p>
<p>If it doesn't come across that way, let me say it here—I don't say all this to suggest anyone owes me anything; they don't. My hope was always that Pasifika would have seen the value in this thing and worked with me on it towards an outcome for our community.</p>
<p>I know there are even more organisations out there now, helping Pasifika towards tech pathways, and that's great. I just know there was nothing quite like what we had with the Pasifika Tech Network.</p>
<p>Onto the next one.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading,</p>
<p>Ron.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>AI-Sovereignty-Governance</category>
            <category>pasifika</category>
            <category>career</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Checking in...]]></title>
            <link>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/checking-in</link>
            <guid>https://www.uncommonengineer.com/blog/checking-in</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Brief check-in thanking paid subscribers and teasing upcoming podcast format for newsletter content. Essential reading for understanding this critical perspecti]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I just wanted to send you a note to say, thank you, for valuing access to my writing enough to part with your hard-earned money…</p>
<p>And to let you know there’s more writing in the pipeline, it’s just been competing with several other things that require brain-space, which, as smart as I think I am, is still limited lol.</p>
<p>If there’s a particular topic you’d be interested in hearing me speak on, or explore, please feel free to contact me, I’m open to ideas.</p>
<p>Also, I’m gonna try the podcast thing soon- which will just be me reading the post out, so you can hear it how I mean it to sound :)</p>
<p>til the next one,</p>
<p>Ron.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>AI-Sovereignty-Governance</category>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>